<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A cap of grey hairs for a green head, or, The fathers counsel to his son, an apprentice in London to which is added a discourse on the worth of a good name / by Caleb Trenchfield.</title>
            <author>Trenchfield, Caleb, 1624 or 5-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 235 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 108 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25830</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09149090</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09149090</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42531</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63124)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42531)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1296:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A cap of grey hairs for a green head, or, The fathers counsel to his son, an apprentice in London to which is added a discourse on the worth of a good name / by Caleb Trenchfield.</title>
                  <author>Trenchfield, Caleb, 1624 or 5-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>209, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for Henry Eversden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fathers and sons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42531:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CAP OF GRAY HAIRS, FOR A GREEN HEAD. OR, The Fathers Counſel To his SON, An Apprentice in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is added, A Diſcourſe on the worth OF A good NAME.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Caleb Trenchfield.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 10.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The memory of the juſt is bleſſed, but the name of the wicked ſhall rot.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>Henry Everſden,</hi> at the end of <hi>Duck-lane</hi> in <hi>Smithfield.</hi> 1671.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42531:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42531:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SON,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving been at ſo much coſt and care to ſet you fairly out, to act your part upon the ſtage of this the preſent world; I was conſulting what might be further done, to give aſſiſtance to your fair come off. And now ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving that you were gone out from under the obumbrage of the Fathers wing, when counſel was at hand as each occaſion did preſent it ſelf, and yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to a ſtanding much more ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, through the great ſtore of power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful temptations; I thought it meet to ſend you up a ſtock of ſuch well-tried advice as might ſerve as a panoply, from whence to fetch ſupplies, as your occaſions ſhould impoſe a need.</p>
            <p>And though ſome Fathers, and of them ſome perſons of great Note, have undertook to give advice unto their Sons; whoſe works in that kind are yet extant; and therefore this may ſeem
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42531:3"/>more needleſs; yet there's not any (that I know of) hath ſtoopt ſo low, to give advice to an Apprentice, but did direct their thoughts to ſuch a pitch, as lay not in the level of the greateſt part of perſons; to whom advice was not leſs needful. However, you'll find here ſome ſtore of things not touched by their obſervation, and ſuch as when experimented, will be approv'd to need your warineſs, and caution. But what concerns you moſt, is not the Doctrine, but the Uſe; for 'tis not hard to give good Counſel, but to take it. Green Heads are apt to think themſelves the wiſeſt; but that were ſtrange, when as our wiſdome (for the moſt part) is bought by experience, and young men are too young to make an ample pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe. You have this advantage then, to have that ſtock, which hath been traded for by elder years, and thoſe too exerciſed not in a few concerns: adde theſe unto your own, and you may be as wiſe, as if you had already lived ſome more years.</p>
            <p>If this care for you turn not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, I'm ſure the error will be found your own; and if that hereby you're
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42531:3"/>not made the wiſer, your follies will be more without excuſe. But I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute theſe my deſigns contrived for your benefit, with my unceſſant pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that God would ever do you good, and be your ſure and everlaſting Guide. For as our Actions ſhould be all done for his Glory; ſo ſhould our enterprizes be all undertaken with the expectance and invocation of the divine aſſiſtance. Therefore as in the diſpoſing of our affairs, reſpect ſhould be had by us that we may be ſerviceable to God in our Generations; ſo ſhould our eyes be up unto him for his bleſſing on us in thoſe affairs, whoſe overflowing hand doth blaſt them, or elſe make them flouriſh; the one or other even as he pleaſeth. And it ſhould be our moſt important care, that we ſo live, as that by our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity we give no cauſe that he ſhould bring a curſe on us and our endeavours.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing therefore which I have to recommend to you, is Religion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God; by which notion I do chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtand, All care to ſave a mans own Soul: for it ſeems an apparent ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationality, there to deſign the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent management of the affairs of this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42531:4"/>preſent life, where a man is utterly regardleſs of thoſe much more impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant concernments of a better. And if the Child in the womb had but the ſame reſentments of the life here, as we have of that which is to come, 'twould be eſteemed ſtrange, if it ſhould be more thoughtful for its eaſie lying the nine moneths there, than its comfortable li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (it may be) an hundred years here. And much more groſs is our vanity and madneſs, in the neglect of thoſe things which are not ſeen, which are eternal; when we only care for thoſe things which are ſeen, which are tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral. But it is not my deſign here, to give you directions in this buſineſs, that would ſwell this little Manual into too great a Bulk; and there are almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable pious labours of Learned men who have largely treated on this ſubject. But there is one main thing, which is in truth much wanting every where, which I have chiefly here to mind you of, to wit,</p>
            <p>That you be ſerious in the matter of Religion: for he that is ſerious, thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of thoſe affairs, according to that vaſt concernment that is in them, will
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42531:4"/>not be much to ſeek in the expedients tending thither; yet let me ſet before you two or three things by way of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Do not buſie your ſelf much about the Controverſal part of Religion, for that ingenders ſtrife, rather than edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and makes a man rather buſily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive, than uſefully practical. Faith and good works they are the things wherein a man can never unprofitably, never too abundantly be imployed. And the truth is, 'ts no hard matter for the talk of Religion, to ſupplant the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of it; nor for a man to ſpeak hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely of that, which he will never do; and like <hi>Seneca,</hi> to praiſe poverty, whileſt he heaps up millions. 'Tis infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely better to be conſcientiouſly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing the plain truths we know, than curiouſly diſputing about thoſe things we know not; rather walking in the good old way of manifeſt holineſs, than in the new affected way of diſputed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion.</p>
            <p>Do not eſpouſe any opinion, faction, or way of men, to be led by them one ſtep farther, than the clear conviction of thine own judgment doth conduct
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42531:5"/>thee. For how great indiſcretion is it to be hurried by the whirl of others mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, into thoſe precipices, whirl depth and dangers thine own conſiderate foreſight did not firſt ſound? And how great an injury is it to that Reaſon which God hath given us, to ſubject our Underſtanding to the Senſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>&amp; jurare in verba Magiſtri,</hi> and like ſilly ſheep to bounſe into no ſmall inordinateneſs, only becauſe we ſaw ſome great Ram leap in before us? And verily 'twould vex one, to ſee thoſe who do deſign to draw diſciples after them, to lead a crew of Gulls into no ſmall puddles, by having obtained the repute of being no meanly underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ganders. For how many hens do we dayly ſee, following that Cock, who hath had the confidence to crow ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on his own dung-hill; out of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of having his right diſputed by the dint of Weapon?</p>
            <p>I confeſs it hath been no impolitick way to wealth and promotion, to be a ſtout abettor of the prevailing faction, and great aſſertor of the opinion in faſhion.</p>
            <p>And we need not go far for examples
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42531:5"/>of thoſe, who by this gale have proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſailed to deſired Dignities. But if the Apoſtle make it a ſmall matter, to give carnal things in exchange for ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual; ſurely 'tis abominable Traffick to give our ſpiritual things for carnal, and abet opinions to fill our purſes, not better our Souls.</p>
            <p>But beſides, 'tis ſeldome but God takes theſe wiſe in their own craftineſs, and brings ſuch a turn which throws them out of Dignities ſhamefully, who brought themſelves in hypocritically.</p>
            <p>Never ingage ſo far in any opinion, or way, as to ſuffer for it, without the clear conviction of thine own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that it is thy duty ſo to do. For though there be a glory in ſuffering, overballancing to ſome humors the loſs and ſmart which accompanies it; and though there be much in a preoccupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted judgment that we do well in ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, eſpecially when we are clap't on the back, and incouraged by thoſe who abet the opnion: Though thus (I ſay) when in hot blood, and in the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the buſineſs, it was not hard to appear gallant in ſome herce incounters; yet when the wounds are ſtark, the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42531:6"/>ſpectators gone, and thou left in thy ſolitudes, and become ſerious, believe me, thy ſpirit will be intolerably dull, if it be not ſerened with a conſcience teſtifying from manifeſt truth, that thou haſt ſuffered according to the will of God.</p>
            <p>But further, under this notion of Religion I have to recommend to you all acts of Devotion and ſervice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God; all care to give unto him the inward adoration of the heart, and the outward worſhip which is well-pleaſing in his ſight. And this advice is the more neceſſary, becauſe the greateſt part of perſons among us, ſuch as are not factiouſly devout, are irreligiouſly profane. For from the one extreme, the moſt of men are run unto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; contenting themſelves with the name of Chriſtians, and nothing but the name. In which reſpect (I think) they are not matcht by any generation of people in the world beſide. For whereas every Nation acknowledgeth ſome God which they worſhip after their manner, with a zealous devotion, even to the prodigal expending of their very lives; how many are there among
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42531:6"/>us, which have not ſo much as a ſhew of Religion, not any Duty performed to God in their Families, not any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of his name, unleſs in curſed Blaſphemy and Oaths? And that wherein cuſtome hath ſo much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, that it is a ſhame not to do it; (I mean giving of thanks at meat) what affected brevity is deſign'd, as if they intended rather a ſcoff of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty, than otherwiſe? As for the attendance upon the Publike ſervice, verily that is as to a Play, more than ought elſe, doing meerly what the Poet ſaith Women came for to the Theatres, <hi>Spectatum veniunt, veniunt ſpectentur ut ipſae:</hi> the ends of moſt, at thoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine imployments, being to ſhew their own braveries, or ſee that of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and the moſt exact account which they there take of any thing, is the new faſhion.</p>
            <p>But do thou, in thy attendance upon Divine Worſhip, ſay, as <hi>Jacob</hi> of <hi>Bethel, How dreadful is this place!</hi> and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the greatneſs of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, who hath profeſſed himſelf to be a jealous God, and therefore moſt obſervant what manner of Addreſſes thou makeſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42531:7"/>to him; doing the duty thou art en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in with all thy might; as well knowing that that God who requireth thou ſhouldeſt love him with all thy heart, expecteth that thou ſhouldeſt apply thy ſelf to his ſervice, with the moſt united intention of all thy facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>And though the Apoſtle ſaith, that we ſhould pray <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceaſing, the heart being always in a frame of calling upon God, and in a continual deſire and expectance of ſupplies from him, in whom all our ſprings are; Yet our ſolemn applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions unto him, in hearing him ſpeak to us, or our ſpeaking to him, ſhould be with that fear and reverence, as ſuits with his infinite and incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible greatneſs. And as our hearing of his Word read or preached, ſhould be not as of the ſound of words, but with obſervation of the importance of the ſenſe: So ſhould our calling upon him, not be the inconſiderate &amp; formal mumbling over a parcel of prayers; but with that faith, affection, and earneſt deſire, as may approve thee to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than a vain babler.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:42531:7"/>
            <p>Neither is Religion onely of great uſe as to the advantages of the world to come, but alſo to the concernments of this preſent life: the Grace of God which bringeth Salvation, teaching us not only to live godly, but alſo righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, and ſoberly.</p>
            <p>Now as I have made it my care to diſpoſe you to ſuch a Maſter, as hath a good report of all men, and I hope of the truth it ſelf, that he is an honeſt good man, and able in his way; from whom you will receive dayly examples of the exerciſe of vertue; and who, as he will expect the duty of a ſervant from you, in your ſervice of him; ſo I know he will perform the duty of a Maſter to you, in your government and inſtruction: So it behooves you now to anſwer the end that was deſigned in your being ſo diſpoſed of, and ſo to take care to be a ſervant now, as that you may be a Maſter hereafter. To which end, it is not a little conducing, to come off the Stage with the clear ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe of having acted the part of a ſervant well: for he that is turniſhed whit that report, goes a great way in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42531:8"/>the ſecond part (I mean) the ſetting up for himſelf.</p>
            <p>He that will thus come off, muſt be much imployed in the exerciſe of thoſe vertues, which greatly tend to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a good name; and the firſt of theſe we may ſay is <hi>Veracity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For not to ſpeak how great a ſin it is by a lie to deny the God of truth, and his omniſcience who knoweth all things; It is not to be imagined, how great a diſrepute is thereby contracted. For we thereby not onely make our ſelves the ſcorn of thoſe that do diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us, but deprive our ſelves of that belief, which we might expect from thoſe which do not. The liar rendring himſelf perpetually ſuſpected, and even then when ſpeaking truth not believed.</p>
            <p>Neither ſhall you find the liar any wiſe anſwered in that deſign of excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelf, which he propoſeth: For beſides that it argues much profaneneſs to back one ſin with another, and make recompence for what was ill done the firſt time, with doing ill the ſecond; it ſeldom proves, but that the falſhood is diſcovered, and what might at firſt be eaſily pardoned, upon a fair con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42531:8"/>is made the ſubject of a ſevere animadverſion, by a repeated guiltineſs, And in very deed, it is very ſeldom. but that a ſoft anſwer, and confeſſion, obtains the diſmiſſion of that offender, whom a lve would have detained unto a future judgment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fidelity</hi> is another virtue ſo eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally neceſſary in this deſign, that to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a good ſervant without it, were to make a man without reaſon. Let it be therefore your principal care to keep your hand undefiled from the touch of whatſoever you cannot juſtly call your own. Neither let any opportunity, or probability of concealment ever tempt you to lay your fingers on that, which your conſcience tells you not, is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantably yours. For a bird of the air will tell the matter, and what is ſo unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly detained, muſt either be with ſhame refunded, or (which is worſe) with impenitency kept, to the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring up of wrath againſt the day of wrath. Beſides obſerve, how great an happineſs it is to be bold-faced in the conſcience of our own integrity in this behalf; when like <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> we are able to preſent a challenge to the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42531:9"/>whole world, if they can charge our hands with any thing that is theirs.</p>
            <p>But it concerns you alſo, to have no confederacy with any that have clam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my hands; no nor any connivence: for it is not the leaſt part of fidelity to thoſe who do entruſt us, to be as their eyes, and ears, to prevent all injurious encroachments. And 'tis eaſie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture, how great a conducement one truſty ſervant is, to the ſtifling the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes, and throwing water upon the gun-powder of thoſe evil deſignes, whereby unfaithful Servants abuſe their Maſters, and ſometimes even blow up their eſtates.</p>
            <p>There is another ſort of <hi>Fidelity,</hi> though not of that conſequence, yet not leſs acceptable to thoſe who ſhall imploy you; when you ſhall be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to their reputations, not onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding all reports and ſpeeches which may caſt upon them any the leaſt blem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh; but at all times interpoſing your ſelf in their vindication, againſt the obloquy of thoſe, who may traduce them.</p>
            <p>And verily, as to ingenious ſpirits, nothing is more dear, than their repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42531:9"/>ſo is there not any thing which endears a ſervant to ſuch Maſters more, than when he ſhall be overheard, either refuting ſuch calumnies whereby their good name was endangered, or giving the moſt favourable interpretation to thoſe juſt allegations to which their weakneſs, or overſight, might render them obnoxious.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Temperance</hi> is the next which here comes to be mentioned; a virtue of that expediency, that ſcarce any bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs is readily done without it: for he who wants this moderator, and too deeply drencheth himſelf in that which is too much, is like a man run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in boots, unfit for any imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For which cauſe <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ſluggard ſhall be cloathed with rags, becauſe he cryes, Yet a little more ſleep, a little more ſlumber.</hi> And truely it is not hard to declame againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate uſe of ſleep, it being indeed, as it were, the abatement of our life, and as either returning us into that condition we were in in our mothers womb, or as anticipating that when in our graves; being as it were to that end ordained, to put us in mind of our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42531:10"/>own infirmity, and that we die dayly. To be ſure, we do not onely deprive our ſelves of ſo much of our lives, as is thus unneceſſarily diſpoſed; but we do alſo cut off from our ſelves ſo much of opportunity to diſpatch our affairs, as is by us this way intemperately ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended.</p>
            <p>In both which reſpects of Health and Wealth, we may alſo adviſe you from intemperance in meats and drink; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch, as moſt certainly decayes the body, and conſumes the purſe. Exceſs in theſe, being not onely a pleaſurable evil, whereby we cut our own throats with no ſmall delight, and put out na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural heat, with throwing on too much fuel. But it is alſo a coſtly vanity, the dainty tooths of ſome, corroding ſo far into their eſtates, as to reach the very vitals; and one mouth being more than enough for ſix pair of hands. For what would ſupply a temperate recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied appetite with what is wholſome, at the price of a few pence, will not allay the itch of one luxurious, with what it ſhall think toothſome, at as many pounds: the one intending the ſatisfying of hunger (which when it is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42531:10"/>done finds an end) the other like the itch of ſcabby parts, the more it is ſcratched, the more deſires it. And this caution deſerves your greater care, being in a City which abounds with fulneſs of bread; whither all the dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Kingdome have their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence; and exceſs in eating is uſhered in with the greateſt ſolemnity and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance (I believe) of any place in the world beſides. The delights of <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſo much talked of, as the enervating poiſon heroick Spirits; being but as <hi>Kick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhawes</hi> to thoſe exceſſes which the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent luxury hath excogiated; wherein the deſign, ſeems by repeated prorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to deal by ſtomacks, as Cock-maſters by their fainting duelliſts, hold them up, that cannot ſtand of themſelves, to a freſh encounter.</p>
            <p>And though this exceſs of eating may be as hurtful to the body, and conſumptive to the purſe; yet it is not in many reſpects ſo pernicious, as that of drink; which by a ſad fatality proves a deluge to Reaſon, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly brings with it a floud of thoſe debaucheries, which render us the ſcorn of children, and deteſtation of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42531:11"/>ſober men. And though I want not reaſons of the higheſt remark, yet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily I want words to importune you to a juſt abhorrency of ſo great a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, whereby we unman our ſelves of the reaſon God hath given us, like ſwine wallowing in our own vomits; and rendering our ſelves both the fitted inſtruments of every iniquity, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of any good counſel which might prevent us. As therefore your inclination now doth ſtand averſe to this vice, ſo let me adjure you, by all that is dear and ſacred, that you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue at the greateſt diſtance from it.</p>
            <p>Here alſo let me put in a caution againſt intemperance and fantaſtickneſs in Apparel; wherein this Nation is ſo immoderate, that they are moſt witty how to be moſt antick. 'Tis not rare to ſee thoſe perſons expoſed like owls, to the ridiculous wonder of ſober men, ſtrut along, as if they drew after them the admiration, and not the laughter of thoſe that ſee them; when pitiful ſouls, they are the <hi>Ignes fatui,</hi> which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent men follow with their ſcorn, and uſually expire in the ſilly imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies of their own vanity. And
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42531:11"/>therefore expenſiveneſs in Apparel, is certainly as great a foolery, as men are guilty of; when at huge rates, they purchaſe thoſe things, for which they are no more valued, than a fore-horſe for his feather. For if Apparel be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Eſtate, the onely eſteem you get thence, is of a prodigal fool; if but equal to it, you have that eſteem without it. For you may obſerve, that the value which we ſet upon perſons (beſide that due to the endowments of their mind) is according to their Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals; and he that hath an ample reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, ſhall be reſpected, however plainly clad: when a fine fellow without, by thoſe that know him, ſhall have no more eſteem, than a poor raſcal on a Stage, though in the array of a Prince: and he that came in to King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth</hi> with an hundred tenements on his back, ſold to make him brave, would have had twice as many hats off the next Term, if he had had the rent of them in his purſe. It is therefore wiſdom to be neat, not gallant; and to wear ſuch apparel as may ſhew you are not ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did, and neglect your ſelf; not ſuch as may make your purſe look thin through
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42531:12"/>the coſt, nor your judgement cenſured for the vanity.</p>
            <p>What comes next to be laid before you, is the art of <hi>Silence;</hi> of no mean conſideration in the quietneſs of your life, and advantage of your affairs. And therefore as in general, that talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ative humour ſhould be avoided, which expoſeth a man very much to the cenſure of others, it being very difficult to talk much and well: the <hi>Greek</hi> Adage being true, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>much ſpeaking is not without much folly.</hi> Neither is it a little hard, ſo to manage that ſlippery inſtrument, as that ſomething ſhall not thence eſcape, which may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted to your prejudice, eſpecially if perſons be talked of whom you cannot commend without envy, nor diſpraiſe without danger. Every one being ſmartly ſenſible of the ſtroak of the tongue; and none being ſo ready to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend for being beaten, as to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged of the beater.</p>
            <p>But 'tis eſpecially dangerous to ſpeak any thing in the diſparagement of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Beauty, or Honour; for they are naturally waſpiſh Creatures, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42531:12"/>apt to take pet; and by how much the more feeble, the more prone to revenge thoſe things, which an elated magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity would overlook, as too inferiour a mark. Through the conſciouſneſs of which imbecility, they lay their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns cloſe, and proſecute their mean concerns with more extreme revenges, than you can eaſily imagine: being ſure to do that at the firſt caſt, which they are ever in fear will not be effected by an after-game; and are fully taught that policie, to ſhoot with Bullets, and not Hail-ſhot; and level their blow at the head, and not the heel. Doing their buſineſs too, after the <hi>Italian</hi> mode; ſo that though their diſguſts, like that of <hi>Juno</hi>'s upon the arbitrement of <hi>Paris, manetalta mente repoſtum,</hi> yet it ſhall not break forth till you are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd; like the cannon giving the blow, after the mark is torn in pieces. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you may obſerve in all ſtory no Vindicts ſo tranſcendent as thoſe of women, clear particularly in <hi>Overburies</hi> Caſe, whom no indearments could ranſome from being a Victime of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minine rage. Neither ſhall you find any thing of a more dire immanity than
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42531:13"/>the <hi>Pariſian</hi> Nuptials on <hi>Bartholomew</hi>-Eve; which yet were hatcht under a <hi>French</hi>-Hood, and not a Helmet: for which cauſe thoſe Fathers of Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion repreſented all the Furies under the notion of women, and expreſly ordered, that <hi>Erinnys</hi> ſhould be <hi>foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minci gencris.</hi> Neither is it a farthing matter, whether what you have ſaid, be true or no; unleſs by how much the truer, by ſo much the more biting: it being with them, as the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> ſaid of <hi>Nero, Quae facere gaudebat, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire gravabatur,</hi> their principal art be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that of concealment; and therefore they hate no dog ſo much, as the blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound.</p>
            <p>But this is not to be underſtood ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally; for there are of that Sex, very many, whoſe ſentiments are ſuitable to the delicacy of their conſtitutions, being as innocent and harmleſs, as the moſt gentle Turtles, whoſe purer ſouls know nothing of ſin, more than what cannot be avoided by common infirmity; and therefore, ſweet creatures, are without any thing of gall; and are far from thoughts of revenge, becauſe they can think none ſo ill, as to deſerve an ill
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42531:13"/>thought of them. To ſpeak any thing which might, though but obliquely, reflect upon ſuch as theſe, were an impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety not to be expiated by the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive acknowledgments. But there are beſides theſe, thoſe whoſe hearts are branded with blackeſt Characters, by frequent commiſſions ſteeling their Conſciences to the perpetration of thoſe villanies, which 'tis their greateſt art to cover over with a different ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance; to which end they rack their curious wits (without doubt the moſt ſublimated of any intelligence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that of Spirits) to the greateſt keenneſs, in inventing expedients to hide that, which they fear not to commit; but hate ſhould be known, and therefore proſecute with as cruel ſpite him that ſhould pretend a diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, as if you had undertaken the publick unplaiſtering of a painted face.</p>
            <p>But you are very much to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, not to diſcover the concerns of that family wherein you live, for every mans houſe is his Caſtle, and ſhould be as his Cabinet; whence nothing ſhould be divulg'd but by his permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42531:14"/>In the reaſon of which we have ſo many examples, even of ſome ſlaves, who have endured the extremeſt tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, rather than diſcover their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſecrets. Neither is it any wiſe fit to babble of thoſe things which you may poſſibly conceive are of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable moment; for he that will indiſcreetly tell any thing, is ever ſuſpected that he will tell every thing. And they that have ſome truth from your mouth to begin upon, will thereon build ſuch ſuperſtructure, as is proportionable to their own imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations: all which they ſtamp cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and paſſable upon the credit of that truth which you at firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</p>
            <p>But eſpecially let what is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to you as a ſecret, be lockt up by you in an incloſure, not to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, but by the key of him that gave it. For moſt intolerable is that va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which leaks out into the next company what was committed by his friend, or is eaſily drawn in to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver what was ſo entruſted; for no man but vilifies that perſon in his own eſtimate, who is looſe-bodied upon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42531:14"/>that account; and judges him a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible ſpunge, whom he finds facile to be ſqueez'd out of what he was ſo charg'd with.</p>
            <p>And here you may alſo take notice, how expedient it is not to be talkative of ſuch deſignes, as are in your thoughts, of bargains to buy, or buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to do; for thereby you give great occaſion for others to prevent you, if they judge it worth the while: and thoſe who come under the reach of your projects, are thereby alarmed to circumvent you, and defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and 'tis no ſmall advantage in every affair, to take thoſe we are to deal with unprovided. For which cauſe the late Uſurpers did repreſent their great concerns as already done, rather than to be done; and there was no talk of what they purpoſed, till 'twas effected. And you may obſerve, that the ſly Fox who ſilently ſnaps his prey, ſhall alone troble the number, that a crew of babbling Beagles ſhall get by their out-cry: and 'tis your cloſe lads who commonly effect thoſe buſineſſes, which your great talkers can never compaſs.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:42531:15"/>
            <p>Know alſo, that though there be a natural proneneſs to boaſt of our own abilities; yet he is very unwiſe that talks of them, or of his own arts. For 'tis one of the greateſt parts of cunning, to endeavour not to be thought ſo: and he that proclaims his own skill, beats the Drum to the alarming thoſe he hath to do with; and ſummons every man to come well provided to deal with him, that declares he goes always furniſhed with a ſword and Buckler. And 'tis the only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit that an opinion of our wit and nimbleneſs begets us, that we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted with that reſolution which lies immoveable on its own baſis; or like an Hedg-hogg, ſhews nothing to the teeth of our art, but its ſharp prickles.</p>
            <p>Nor is it fit to talk of our expectances, nor of our hope of ſuch ſucceſſes, which depend upon the good will of others, which are ſet <hi>in lubrico;</hi> and if we fall from ſuch hopes ſo diſcovered, we fall as much in our reputations, as if our caſuality had been real; and expoſe our ſelves as much to the deriſion of others. And ſuch imaginary diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42531:15"/>are not ſeldom retorted on us, as the true returns of our own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs: and 'tis but a juſt confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that others take in this kinde to deny us, when they ſee us ſo rich in hopes, but not ſo in performance. However, he that antedates his own en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, and pre-occupies them in his diſcourſes, doth truely according to the Proverb, <hi>Reckon his chicken before they are hatcht;</hi> And, <hi>Sell the bears skin ere it be caught.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But be warily ſilent in all ſuch things as are bandyed in difference between others: for he that blows the coals in others ſtrifes, ſhall be ſure to have the ſparks fly in his mouth. It being hard to make even ſuch an amicable interpoſition as ſhall not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of a ſiniſter interpretation. All men almoſt being led by their paſſions and prejudices, and their own inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt; and ſcarce a man that will weigh his own cauſe in the ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Juſtice. And therefore you will be neceſſitated in ſuch caſes either to deny your own reaſon, and be tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about at the pleaſure of others, or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42531:16"/>expoſe your ſelf to the diſguſts of thoſe, who judge of your ſentiments, not by the truth and reaſon of them, but by their own paſſions.</p>
            <p>But it is vilely odious to be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument by incentive relations to add fuel to the animoſities of diſſenting parties, and be a tale-bearer to keep up that fewd, which might otherwiſe expire through want of nouriſhment. For beſide that ſuch practices uſually prove pernicious, and they that deal in them, as it were, hold a fox by the ears, and ſeldom part without a ſnap, or a ſcratch, if not worſe: It is the Devils work to blow the coal of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention; and on the contrary, the peace-makers are reckoned a part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſeven Beatitudes.</p>
            <p>'Tis therefore every ones duty to bury all corroding language in eternal oblivion: and it will be your wiſdom to have your tongue dipt in Oyl al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, in Vinegar never: I mean, not to convey any ſuch relations as ſhall have a bitterneſs in them; nor give any ſuch anſwers in your own cauſe, which ſhall not be lenitive. For how much a ſoft anſwer pacifieth wrath, I
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42531:16"/>believe you need not look back upon antient examples, how thereby <hi>Gideon</hi> quieted the <hi>Ephraimites,</hi> or <hi>Abigail David,</hi> when <hi>Nabals</hi> churliſh anſwer had not a little incenſed him; your own occaſions will give you experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence enough of this nature: neither will there need much to perſwade you, if in ſuch occurrents you conſult your reaſon, and not your paſſion. For the truth is, it is a fooliſh praefractorineſs that cannot ſtoop to a ſubmiſſion; and 'tis ſurely no leſs then madneſs to think that what was ill done by caſual over-ſight, will be made amends for by a ſtubborn reply.</p>
            <p>And here 'twill not be impertinent to adviſe you to be of a meek and calm converſation, by no means apt to take pet at matters of leſs moment, for ſuch captious perſons are like the weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock, which every winde diſturbs, and diſpoſes into a different Aſpect; by which, as they contract no ſmall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſs to themſelves, ſo they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come very unacceptable to others. But where there is juſt cauſe given, 'tis much better to let the waſps alone, then by contending with them to bring a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42531:17"/>ſwarm about your ears: Yet much more inconvenient is it to be a man of ſtrifes, and to ſtudy occaſions to quarrel with others; ſo that none can come neer you without a collar of prickles. For by that means you'll be lookt upon as a fire in all companies, who make ready the hearth of a dry burnt diſcourſe for your entertainment, and ſet out of the way, as too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtible to come neer you, what is free and debonair.</p>
            <p>And beſides too, ſuch tempers, by their frequent colliſion, do ſtrike fire out of thoſe flints, where otherwiſe none would have appeared, and raiſe up enemies out of that duſt, which if not ſtir'd, would never have flown in their eyes.</p>
            <p>But it is an hundred times better to ſtudie the good will of all, rather then to make an enemy of any; and to be of that obliging ſpirit, as to gain the affection of every one (except, as <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> ſaith of <hi>Sejanus</hi>) <hi>Quorum voluntas non niſi ſcelere quaeritur:</hi> Whoſe kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is to be had not but by a conſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation in wickedneſs. For there is not a Creature ſo contemptible, which may
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42531:17"/>not be ſomething beneficial, and whoſe friendſhip may not be rather valuable then its enmity. And therefore kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes done meet with requitals many times beyond what could be expected; and 'tis a ſtory well known, <hi>That he who prov'd a Chirurgion to the lame Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, had his life afterwards ſaved by the ſame Lyon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And verily, how far a conſtant affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility prevails for the gaining of men, make trial, and you'll finde: for daily experience ſhews, that we make thoſe creatures our play-fellowes, which are manſuete and gentle; but keep at a diſtance thoſe, which are fierce and cruel: and the ſurly grim Maſtiff lyes without doors, when we make a Lapdog of him tha tis affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>What I have next to adviſe you to, is, the practice of Frugality, a virtue expedient for all, but chiefly for you, who like the Silk-worm, muſt ſp n your riches out of your own boſon, having ſuch mean expectations of helps from abroad. That that I have to leave you, being but little at the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42531:18"/>moſt; and if I had much, and you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the eldeſt, might challenge the greateſt ſhare, yet there are nine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, and a poſſibility of more, which muſt all be furniſhed out into the world as well as you: and well 'twill be, if God give me life and ability to do that. So that the caſe ſtands with you, as in Military affairs, where 'tis running but once, and no hopes of your ever rallying, if you be once routed. I have furniſhed you into the way that you are in, not onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my power, but in truth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond it; therefore if you ſhipwrack now, <hi>conclamatum eſt.</hi> Be careful then to play your fore-game well, for an after-game will have no place with you; and ſuch wit will be but <hi>Phrygian</hi> wiſdom, where they are wiſe too late. There will be no hopes of a ſecond ſetting forth, if your firſt miſcarry. And in truth, no man takes that courſe, but goes upon great diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages. For like thoſe who intend to ſow Corn on woody grounds, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſe that Husbandry which is common to every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rop, but alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id out of the way with much labour thoſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42531:18"/>buſhes and rubbiſh which cumber the the Land: So you will finde your ſelf not onely to colluctate with thoſe difficulties which uſually occur in every deſigne, but alſo with thoſe preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices which every one will take up, upon your firſt miſcarriage; and you'll finde it much more hard to repair a credit once impaired, then to keep that in a flouriſhing greenneſs which was never blaſted.</p>
            <p>Be ſure therefore to go out into the world like a ſheet of clean paper, where no blurs or ſcribblements are to be diſcern'd; but let your reputation be like that Virgin purity, not ſtain'd with any thing which may render you ſuſpected to the time to come. For that is the beſt frugality which is ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of our credit, which can never be cuſtodited with too great jealouſie, nor expended but with the greateſt loſs. Nor yet think that credit which is gotten with the expence of mony, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs God ſhall ſo bleſs you, as that it ſhould be a ſhame to you not to be No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: For he that expects repute, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a good eſtate, by being ſparing, is like the man who would bring his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:42531:19"/>horſe to live with nothing; ſo he that would get credit by ſpending high, whilſt his Eſtate is low, doth but blow a Bladder, which will burſt with a ſtink. And be ſure of this, that the firſt ſtep to reputation (next to do vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly) is to have ſomething: and therefore lay out no money, but what neceſſity extorts, or ſuch conveniencie as will be ſure to return with a good <hi>Cargo:</hi> For obſerve the old Rule, that <hi>A penny ſav'd is two pence got;</hi> and the way to much is by a little, for the greateſt ſum which can be imagined, was begun in a penny; and 'tis worth your minding, how much he had for his horſe, who ſold him but for an half-penny a nail doubled.</p>
            <p>And therefore be skill'd in that part of Arithmetick, which is Addition, and not Subſtraction: for when there is an inclination to take out, and you think 'tis but a ſmall matter; conſider how many dry blows the poor Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-man gives, to earn no more in an whole day, to ſuſtain his Family with bread, then thou ſquandereſt away on thy ſweet tooth, or thy vanity.</p>
            <p>And take notice, that as the moſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42531:19"/>ample Structure had but one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> at the firſt, a corner-ſtone at the beginning: So be certain, that an eſtate is caſilyer propagated from ſomething, though never ſo ſmall, then from nothing; and he that hath one ſhilling, may much ſooner get five, then he a penny, who hath not one farthing. Therefore that Graſier who left behinde him ſome thouſands of yearly Revenue, took care to ſave when he was a poor Drover ſo much, as bought a Calf to begin with. And you may obſerve, there is ſtill the ſame proportion from ſaving a little to make it more; and he that is not fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal in what is ſmall, no wiſe deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to be truſted with much.</p>
            <p>But this is of eſpecial conſideration, if you ſhall be intruſted with the keeping of your Maſters Caſh: For on that look with as jealous an eye, as you would do on a plague-ſore, if a thought come in your minde of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying one penny of it for your own uſe. For know, all that is there muſt be accounted for; and 'twill be ten to one oddes between the eaſineſs of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out, and of returning it back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:42531:20"/>
            <p>A very fit Partner for Frugality, is Induſtry; That what is by ſparing ſaved, may be with diligence improved; and what is ſo improved, be again ſpared. For frugality alone is but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle getting; but joyned with indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, is double: like thoſe beams of the Sun, which by a repercuſſion from the earth, make that heat not to be indured, which would be hardly warmth other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. And there, where much cannot be done at once, diligence effects it by degrees, producing by a frequent repetition as great an heat, as more vaſt abilities but leſs active. And it hath been obſerved, that it is not leſs gainful to Navigate in a ſmall Veſſel, which makes quick and frequent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns, then in that which returns but ſeldom, though deeply laden. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> directs the ſluggard to go to the Bee and Ant; which infirm creatures plainly ſhew how much the aſſiduity of an indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious labour can effect. And verily 'tis an ill homour, when becauſe our means ſuit not with our ends, we will not purſue thoſe ends, which ſuit with our means; and becauſe we cannot do
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42531:20"/>what we will, we will not do what we can; depriving our ſelves of what is within our power, becauſe we cannot do the things that are above our power: When indeed that's the way to do much more then we can, by doing the many littles that we are able.</p>
            <p>And this induſtry truely effects things beyond our own expectations, when we are not diſcouraged by diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, but incited; and throw not up the buſineſs as deſperate, becauſe not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently pervious. And let me tell you, of all tempers there's none more to be avoided, the edge of whoſe activity is ſoon abated: for they vilely deſpond at thoſe things as impoſſible, which a more tough diligence doth eaſily ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate. For which cauſe, when the Hiſtorian had reckon'd up the many difficulties and dangers which <hi>Coſmus</hi> that firſt Duke of <hi>Etruria</hi> had to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict with, in his Infant-government; he concludes with this <hi>Epiphonema: Haec omnia alioqui inexpugnabilia Coſmus patientia &amp; induſtria ſua facile vicit.</hi> And verily 'tis no wiſe the part of a man, <hi>ſuccumbere difficultatibus,</hi> and give up the Set, becauſe the Cards prove
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42531:21"/>croſs, but by a generous <hi>antiperiſtaſis,</hi> be hotteſt in our proſecutions, when the coldeſt air blows on our deſigns; and like true Spur-nags, <hi>amniti clivo,</hi> ſtrain hardeſt againſt the Hill; or like Thunder, tear it there moſt, where we meet with the ſturdieſt and moſt rug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Oak. You need never fear but even the talleſt Cedar will fall at your foot, to whoſe root you applyed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant ſtrokes. On which conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I was much taken with his device, who plac'd for his Impreſs a pair of Compaſſ's, with this Motto, <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia &amp; labore;</hi> the one foot being fixt, the other in motion.</p>
            <p>Beſides, let me tell you, that nothing ſhall conciliate to you more friends, while you are a ſervant, then an indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious officiouſneſs, whilſt you are ready to do what the looks and nods of others intimate that they have a minde to: For as we love mettle in Brute creatures, and take delight when Dogs or Horſes ſhew their ready mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at our whiſtle or chirrup; ſo there's nothing we take more pleaſure in, then a diligent and willing ſervant: for he merits no thanks that doth what
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42531:21"/>he is bidden, which otherwiſe would be exacted; but we ſet an eſtimate on him, as exceeding our expectations, who by his readineſs, as it were, anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipates our commands.</p>
            <p>Neither let it moleſt thee, to do thoſe ſervices which are mean, if they be honeſt: For there is nothing vile, but what is wicked; nor cauſe to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of that, which is not facinorous. In the ſenſe of which, we finde <hi>Fabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> that illuſtrious <hi>Roman,</hi> then tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own Gridiron, when the <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite</hi> Ambaſſadors came to petition him for peace. And the truth is, 'tis the meer effect of our pride and vanity, that we ſtamp thoſe things as dede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corous, which are good: for <hi>bonum &amp; honeſtum</hi> are terms convertible; and the Philoſopher defines that <hi>honeſtum, quod honore dignum eſt.</hi> Hence it is that very ſlight perſons among us ſcorn to put their hands to that, which former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kings Daughters made not dainty of. And you may take notice that ſhe is ſet out to us as skill'd in Cooke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, whoſe Brother was <hi>Solomon</hi> in all his glory: but this is the abjectneſs of the age we live in, that idleneſs
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42531:22"/>is an ornament, and the greateſt Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is to do nothing; when as 'tis action onely that is noble; and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Celeſtial bodies are in continual motion, but he that is moſt high, is <hi>puriſſimus actus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next principal conſideration wherein your care is requiſite, is the choice of your Company, wherein e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very perſon receives as great an allay, both in his reputation and diſpoſition, as waters which paſs through Minerals do, in their taſtes and operations: For we ſee it common, for the world to judge what men are by their familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities. And that it ſhould be ſo, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the moſt natural reaſon: for we ſee that all things avoid that which is heterogeneous; and not onely Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, but even conflated Metals eject out of their ſubſtances the leſs ſolid parts: and the liquid bodies of Water and Oyl, are as preciſe in their ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: ſo that as they are all concord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in general principles, ſo are they each as ſchiſmatical in their private natures; whereby they not onely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their ſpecifical differences, but
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42531:22"/>prevent a confuſion, and final reducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their Original <hi>Choas.</hi> Hence we ſee that promiſcuous commixtures are Monſters in Nature; and as what God hath joyned, he will have none to put aſunder: ſo what he hath thus put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder, will he that none ſhould joyn together. And for this cauſe we read thoſe Analogical injunctions, not to Plow with an Ox and an Aſs, nor wear Garments of Linſey and Woolſey mixt together. I have ſaid all this, onely to let you ſee, how impoſſible 'twill be for you to be thought a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of integrity, whilſt you converſe with thoſe that are vitious: And this the rather, becauſe we ſee that all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons affect ſuch as are like themſelves, or thoſe that they may make ſuch; and if you be neither, you either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them as being different, or are condemned by them, becauſe of your difference; and you will finde the ſame cenſure paſt upon you, by all that make judgement of you.</p>
            <p>But you will alſo finde that the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of evil company, is not leſs then the diſcredit. In matters criminal it many times falls out, that our laws
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42531:23"/>involve a guilt, not onely upon the principal Actors, but alſo upon all the company; as in matters of riot and murther. And in caſes of treaſon even ſilence is capital; and in ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany you'll be ingaged, either to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray your friends life, or expoſe your own. Thus <hi>Jaureguius</hi> who attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the murther of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> did not onely bring deſtruction upon himſelf, but on <hi>Venerus</hi> alſo, who though he dreaded to commit the fact, yet kept his counſel that attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it: and the diſcovery of the laſt was made meerly by obſervation, that he was ſeen keep company with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
            <p>But this is not the greateſt danger that evil company brings with it; a deeper miſchief is, that it depraves the minde, and leaves that tang and filth upon the intellectuals and affections, as is not to be abſters'd without much ado by better counſels. And the fata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of this miſchief is ſeen by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion of it upon the pureſt mindes: <hi>Joſeph</hi> having learn'd in <hi>Egypt</hi> to ſwear by the life of <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> And the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral proneneſs that is in us to evil, makes
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:42531:23"/>us ſpungy to receive this unhappy tincture, and ſpreads the venome of it at ſuch a rate, that there are few that finde an antidote ſtrong enough to prevent it. And the diſmal overthrows of many, coming out into the world well diſpoſed, who have been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fligated hereby, ring ſo ſhrill a peal to all that are obſerving, as that we may well condemn him as brutiſh, who is not affected with it. For if you beſpeak thoſe whoſe fortunes are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored, and ask the reaſon why they are ſo, ſcarce one of them but ſhall tell you, that it was evil company that did it.</p>
            <p>There being therefore an innate propenſity in man to aſſociation; Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choriſm being an affect rather of muſt and melancholy, then of choice and election: It being alſo a part of our belief, the Communion of Saints; which conſiſteth not onely in that of the ſpirit, but alſo in perſonal converſe. And Earl <hi>Goodwyns</hi> obſervation of the Confeſſors Cup-bearer, when he ſtumbled with the one foot, and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered himſelf with the other, ſhewing that we have need of the aſſiſtances of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42531:24"/>one another: <hi>For if one fall, the other ſhall help his fellow; but woe be to him that is alone.</hi> 'Tis not therefore the leaſt part of our wiſdom, to make choice of ſuch company, as may be of uſe to us, and not an hindrance in our concerns.</p>
            <p>It is therefore good to chuſe ſuch for your familiars, as (if otherwiſe well qualified) excel in their Way: for as it is a felicity by fate beſtowed on ſome to lead the Cry in every Art and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ingenious Myſterie; ſo there is an innate diſpoſition in ſuch, <hi>ad captandam laudem,</hi> to skim off the Cream of their abilities, and beſtow them as a largeſs upon the company they converſe with; by which means you may obtain thoſe excellencies in Epitome, which they got together with much rubbiſh and cumber. We read therefore, that upon this account the rarer Artiſts of ancient time in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, Zography and Sculpture, thought it worth the while to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take long and dangerous peregrination<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into forraign parts, onely to converſe with thoſe whom fame reported to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel. And without doubt theſe walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:42531:24"/>Libraries are of the greateſt uſe; and knowledge never comes in more richly fraighted, then when it ſets ſail from ſuch continents. 'Tis therefore obſerved, that <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt King of <hi>France,</hi> though he came to the Crown young and unlearned; yet by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the diſcourſes or Learned men, (whom he would always have about him) he attained ſo great ability, as exceeded the proportion of the moſt learned Princes of his time. And I my ſelf knew a perſon taken raw from his ſtudies (being choſen into the Houſe of Commons before he was twenty one) and who from that time very much laid aſide reading; yet by aſſociating himſelf with the moſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men, contracted ſo great a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie, that I have heard him diſcourſe of Philoſophical and Theological con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, as much to my admiration, as it was beyond what I did expect. And I alſo obſerved, that he did greatly vindicate himſelf from that contempt which his youth might ſubject him to, by his accompanying with ſuch perſons as were eſteemed wiſe: for the world could not but conclude, that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42531:25"/>he either was wiſe, or would ſoon be ſo, whoſe company was ſuch. And you will ſinde this a rare advantage in converſing with knowing men, that you will have at hand thoſe who are able to adviſe you, and willing too, if you be but ſo to take it. For there is a natural indulgence that every know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſon hath over thoſe that are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, which makes them willing and ready to enlarge to them the relief of good counſel, when they need it. And if counſel be the ſtrength of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, it can be of no leſs uſe in our private concerns, if God give us an heart to ask and take it: for when young men are adviſed by thoſe like themſelves, giddy headed, and precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate (which commonly they like beſt, becauſe it ſuits their humours) they are intangled like young <hi>Rehoboam</hi> in thoſe incumbrances, whence they cannot explicate themſelves by a too late repentance: therefore take ſuch for your companions, who have already ſow'd their wilde oats, and are by long hunting grown too ſtanch to ſet an haunt; by which means you'll reap the benefit of their dear-bought experience, and prevent your own.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:42531:25"/>
            <p>But chiefly take care to fix upon ſuch company, who are perſons ſtudious of their reputations, men not of a dirty and degenerous temper: For ſome there are, whom nature hath moulded up of the courſeſt clay; whoſe not onely brains repreſent meer rubbiſh, but their very diſpoſitions are of thoſe ſordid <hi>faeces,</hi> which give a tendencie to condeſcend to the moſt ignoble and abject things; whence they'll ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver think much (howſoever vilely) to abuſe, or betray you; when as thoſe who are of an elate and generous ſpirit, have a natural reluctancie to thoſe things which they judge un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy; and are hardly induc'd by the extremeſt neceſſity, to comply with that, which degenerate tempers never make dainty of.</p>
            <p>And upon this account alſo, never ſort your ſelf with ſuch perſons as are below you; for as their reputations will not bear an equal ballance with yours, ſo muſt yours be as much depreſt, as may make it even with theirs; and ſo muſt your expences be as much beyond your own proportion, as their quality is below that which you pretend to: and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:42531:26"/>they will have a confidence to ſlip their heads out of the collar, and leave you to pay all, as if they had done you a kinde of courteſie, in acknowledging your ſuperiority. And 'tis pretty to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how ſuch will claw the itch of your petty ambition with ſuch titles of dignity as they think will pleaſe you, till they have laid you in a ſweat, and made your pores open, and you become melted to effund according to their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</p>
            <p>But above all, avoid ſuch company as are given to drink; for <hi>with whom are wounds without cauſe, but with them that are mighty to drink ſtrong drink?</hi> The drunken man being <hi>fera humana ſpecie,</hi> and therefore ſuch are as unfit for converſe as ſhe-Bears and Lyons, who conſcious of their own ferity, walk alone; while more manſuete Creatures aſſociate themſelves in Flocks and Herds. <hi>Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> ſlain by <hi>Alexander,</hi> and an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred more examples, tell what a Devil is drink; which if it raign any where in the poſſeſſed moſt, it is in our own Country; where they ply their buſineſs beyond compare, and are computed to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42531:26"/>drink more Sack in a year, then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nation doth in three. And though the German did bear away the Bell for drinking; yet it was rather long, then much, being content to pelt his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my at a diſtance: Whereas we are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the modern way of fight, altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for down-blows, being impatient till the oppoſite have a total rout. The drinking of Healths too, being a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne like that of the ſervants of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> at the Pool of <hi>Gibeon,</hi> where they took each other by the Beards, and every one ſmote his fellow under the fifth rib, that they fell down together. If therefore you love your body, your ſoul, your credit, or your purſe, let ſuch perſons be impriſon'd (for the moſt part they are) in the Tavern or Ale-houſe, and do not you come neer them.</p>
            <p>Neither let ſuch be your aſſociates as have been nefarious, or have a brand of guilt upon them; for judgement, though it be ſlow, yet 'tis ſure. And though God have long patience, yet he hath long hands too, and reacheth the guilty at a great diſtance, between the ſin and the puniſhment; which doth not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:42531:27"/>ſeldom involve with it, after the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> mode, their familiars too. Neither do we read any other immediate cauſe of the death of <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> then that he was in the company of King <hi>Joram,</hi> then, when God was executing judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the houſe of <hi>Ahab.</hi> In the ſenſe of which, ſtory tells of St. <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle, that he run out of the Bath into which the Heretick <hi>Cerinthus</hi> came, leſt, as <hi>Corah</hi> and his company, he ſhould be involv'd with him in the ſame judgement. For which cauſe we read of that advice, <hi>Come out of her my people, and be ye not partakers of her ſins, leſt ye be partakers alſo of her plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let ſuch be your company, as for whoſe ſakes God may bleſs you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; ſuch as <hi>Joſeph,</hi> of whom 'tis ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.5. <hi>That after the time that Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph was made overſeer of Potiphars houſe, that God bleſſed the Egyptian for Joſephs ſake: and the bleſſing of the Lord was upon all that he had, in the houſe, and in the field.</hi> And verily, when we read that God would have ſpared five Cities, for the ſake but of ten perſons, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. and that God did
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:42531:27"/>ſpare one of them for but the conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie of <hi>Lot, Gen.</hi> 19.21. we cannot ſufficiently take a ſeantling how far the intereſt of a good man doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon the Almighty; and what an advantage it is to have a ſhare in their prayers, who have ſo much of favour in the Court of Heaven. But beſides, conſider what a benefit it is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted in the ways that are good, by the ſplendor of the vertue of thoſe that are our familiars; to have ſuch about us as ſhall be ready to ſay, <hi>Come let us go up to the houſe of the Lord;</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thee with motions of well-doing, inſtead of thoſe, who ſhall play the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils part, and tempt thee to evil.</p>
            <p>Now in thy converſation with thy familiars, be adviſed in a few things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let not thy friendſhip to them induce thee at any time, to do that which is evil. The ſaying of St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> may well be applyed, <hi>Amicus Plato, amicus Cicero, ſed magis amicus Chriſtus.</hi> The greateſt friendſhip is to be uſeful for heaven. And where the higheſt relations wherein nature hath obliged us, intrench upon that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42531:28"/>we have a warrant to ſuperſede our complyance: <hi>For he that loveth father or mother more then me, is not worthy of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let not thy affection over-bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance thy prudence, and draw thee to things prejudicial to thy credit, or dangerous to thy eſtate: For he is none of thy friend, that would injure thy reputation; nor art thou thine own, if thou wouldeſt damage thine own concerns for another. Friendſhip in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is a ſacred thing, and deſerves our deareſt acknowledgement; nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one thing is there, wherein a man ſhews himſelf more a man: But alas, (that I may ſpeak like a School-maſter) <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi gentium, quo terrarum abiit?</hi> If thy ſpirit ſhould be ſo generous, as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage thee beyond thine own intereſt, in the relation of a friend; where wilt thou finde a correlative? Ancient ſtory tells indeed of a <hi>Damon</hi> and <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias, Pylades</hi> and <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> which mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually contended which ſhould dye for other; and Talkative <hi>Greece</hi> hath not been ſparing to tell their praiſes: But now <hi>terras Aſtraea reliquit.</hi> And the preſent age is ſo far from this kinde of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42531:28"/>friendſhip, that it is hardly found re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſible in common gratitude; but moſt men then ſhake off their friends, when they have no need of their friends, or their friends have need of them. Beſides, if you go to <hi>Ludgaie</hi> or the <hi>Counters,</hi> you ſhall not finde ſo many perſons blaming the prodigali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of themſelves, as curſing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude of their friends; who left them in the lurch, when then they had drawn them in to be obliged. And verily 'tis a pitiful ſolace for a man, whom ſuretiſhip hath made ſure, and intricated in the confinements of a loathſome priſon, to conſider, that he is become ſo, for thoſe who frollick it in that liberty, which they obtain'd by bringing him into the net; or that the world ſhould ſay of him, he was a man of a good nature, and no bodies foe but his own.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Diſcover not thoſe concerns to any of thy familiars, which may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert either to thy damage, or diſcredit, if preſent friendſhip ſhall be changed into unexpected enmity: For 'tis a pitiful and precarious life, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the taciturnity of another;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42531:29"/>and that is a ſlender credit which holds by the weak thred of anothers ſilence; who may diſcloſe thy counſel, either by a natural talkative humour, or by the power of Wine, or a deſigne to oblige another by thy betraying: For beſides that there is an impoſſibility in ſome tempers to ſtand out a ſiege, and not be expugn'd, when cloſely ply'd, as we ſee <hi>Sampſon</hi> himſelf twice in this kinde routed; ſo is it a miſerable captivity to lye at the mercie of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and at his diſcretion to be hang'd, drawn and quartered, with thoſe very inſtruments which were of thy own ſupplying. And men gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally upon ſuch advantages are as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious, as a Maid that is heir to her Miſtreſs; and take pleaſure to make that yoke pinch and wring, into which thine own folly thruſt thy head, and from whence thou haſt not confidence enough to pull it out.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Reſerve to thy ſelf always a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of breaking company; and give up the purſuit, when the Cry hunts not according to thy judgement, or thy private concerns ſound a retreat: For as it is little prudence to buy, by
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42531:29"/>what another bids; ſo is he as little wiſe, that to keep pace with anothers expences, will put his own purſe out of breath. And verily, as I have thought it unjuſt that another ſhould force me to pledge an whole one, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he began it, without reſpect had whether my body or head will bear it; ſo I think 'tis then wiſdom to leave thy friend, when he proves an <hi>Ignis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus,</hi> and would lead thee into a quag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, intangle thee in conteſts and animoſities not eaſily explicated; or, expect that thou for company ſhould bleed as many ounces as he; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated veins of whoſe eſtate may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low phlebotomy, when thine wants juyce of Raiſons. Therefore ballance thou thine expences, not by the poiſe of anothers ſpending, but by the juſter weight of thine own abilities; and think it good manners then to break company, when to put on were like the accompanying with a foul woman, for which thou muſt dearly ſmart af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards.</p>
            <p>But be eſpecially adviſed, not to have any familiarity with the Maid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervants
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:42531:30"/>of the family where you are, more then what conduceth to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patching of general affairs, and ſuch an affability as is common and due to all: for thoſe kinde of cattle have commonly the Stuttle-bee, and are as weary of a ſingle life, as Nuns of their Cloiſters, and therefore catch at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry appearance of a match; and if you ſhew them any kindneſs more then ordinary, they interpret it affection, and make no dainty to challenge you upon that account: wherein if you cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpond not, they hate you worſe then an old decayed woman doth a young flouriſhing beauty. And therefore they rake Hell to finde out inventions to reck their ſpite on you, and value not how they wound their own repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, ſo that they might ſtick yours through it; like <hi>Richard</hi> the Third, who ſcrupl'd not to make his Mother an whore, that he might prove his Brother illegitimate. Neither will their malice thus have its bellyful, but refuſeth ſatiety till you be ruined. Of which the City of <hi>London</hi> hath given too many, and too pertinent examples, where have been thoſe, who by falſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:42531:30"/>accuſations have brought thoſe young men to ſhameful <hi>exits,</hi> whom they could not bring down to their unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy deſignes.</p>
            <p>There is therefore ſcarce any ſubject deſerves your more abundant caution, unleſs it be the treachery of a fellow-Prentice; who if he be facinorous, you may well hang up <hi>votivas tabulas,</hi> if you do eſcape him: For the Devil is not a much more cunning tempter, then ſuch an one proves, whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne is to leſſen his own crime by your copartnerſhip, or to facilitate the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centions of his wickedneſs by thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation; wherein he congratulates himſelf in this at leaſt, that he ſhall have company in his puniſhment, and that thou art involv'd in the ſame condemnation: Though his deſigne be, by thy betraying to excuſe himſelf, and expoſe thee, like the Turkiſh <hi>Aſapi,</hi> to blunt the edge of the rage of the offended. Therefore incredible are the Artifices that thoſe blouded miſcreants have to betray innocent Lads, and decoy them into deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And happy is he whom God keeps, and indues with ſo much prudence as
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42531:31"/>to avoid the danger: But if ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current ſhould befal you, be ſetled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the baſis of faithfulneſs and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty; and like the German, when he hath to deal with the nimble Italian, be reſolv'd that nothing ſhall raviſh thee from thoſe principles of Truth and Juſtice, which thy judgement is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of.</p>
            <p>To this advice concerning your company, I may ſubjoyn that which relateth to your diſcourſe, wherein obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That your diſcourſe be rather little then much; for <hi>a fool is known by his much ſpeaking:</hi> and it is much better to be eſteemed too moroſe and reſerv'd, then by an impertinen babling, to be the ſubject of others deriſion; beſides the danger of ſpeaking that which may be queſtioned, cannot be recall'd; whereas, <hi>Little ſaid may be ſoon amended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Let it be rather free then affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for there is nothing acceptable of this ſort that is not natural; for a very clown in his own language comes off better, then he that by a Romantick
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:42531:31"/>Bumbaſte doth thunder-thump his hearer into an <hi>aequilibrium</hi> between ſcorn and wonder.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let it be rather wiſe then witty, for much wit hath commonly much froth; and 'tis hard to jeſt, and not ſometimes jeer too; which many times ſinks deeper then was intended or expected; and what was deſign'd for mirth, ends in ſadneſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let it be of that Virgin-parity, which knows no ſtain of that which is obſcene: for if <hi>evil communications corrupt good manners,</hi> 'tis in nothing more, then if they be filthy. And as it is a double iniquity to talk filthily of what was done wickedly; ſo is he juſtly condemned as vile, whoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is obſcoene; becauſe <hi>out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Let not thy diſcourſe be to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride the infirmities, or natural imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of another: For in this caſe, what our Lord ſaid to the accuſers of the woman, may be ſaid to all: <hi>He that is without ſin, let him throw the firſt ſtone.</hi> There being no man that blames another, but himſelf comes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:42531:32"/>the laſh in ſome other kinde. It being as natural for men to erre, as to be; and the pureſt Gold of upright men, that ever we read extant, had yet ſomething of an allay. And no doubt but thine own conſcience will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thy ſelf, while thou art the ſharp reprehender of anothers folly. Beſides, it argues a dirty temper, to be ſo Sive-like, as to let paſs the finer Flour, and take pleaſure onely to toſs about the Bran, and refuſe, which even the beſt Wheat is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</p>
            <p>But to make a ſcoff of natural de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, is to make a mock of the God of nature; who acts nothing in vain, or without its reaſon. It might (it may be) be ſomewhat excuſable for thee to deride the wants of another, if thou hadſt been the workman in thine own compoſure; but while that thou wer't <hi>fearfully and wonderfully made,</hi> and now <hi>canſt not add one cubit to thy Stature:</hi> So ſhould anothers defects be the motive of thy thankfulneſs, and not the object of thy laughter; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that thy perfection is the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:42531:32"/>not of thine own care, but the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine goodneſs.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Do not concern thy ſelf in thy diſcourſe, with the publick manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of affairs of State: For it is a kinde of ſerious madneſs, to intereſt our ſelves in the diſpoſure of thoſe things which are ſo much above us, in the judgement whereof we are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally deceived: It being the intent of States-men to reſerve their deſignes conceal'd, and ſtudy to appear what they leaſt intend. But ſhouldſt thou be in the right, thou art never like to be askt thy counſel; and ſo all thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance is but to make a man of clouts for thy ſelf to play with. But the humour of ſome is abominable, to murmur at Authorities, and pleaſe themſelves in complaining of their Superiours: Whereas 'tis the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal part of ſubjection, to ſubmit our ſelves to the diſcretion of thoſe that rule us; and the firſt ſtep to Rebellion, is, when inſtead of doing commands, we diſpute them. The beſt way to prevent the evil effects of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is, not to quarrel with their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, but amend our own. For as
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:42531:33"/>that Engliſhman anſwered ſeriouſly, who (when the Engliſh were driven out of <hi>France,</hi> in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, being upbraidingly askt by a Frenchman, when they intended to return into <hi>France</hi> again) ſaid, <hi>When your ſins are greater then ours:</hi> So will the removing of evil government (when at any time God ſhall bring it) be, not the effect of thy murmur, but repentance; for which cauſe the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian doth well reckon up evil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates among the effects <hi>Divinae acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis,</hi> as Famines and Peſtilences, which we cannot otherwiſe prevent, but by repenting.</p>
            <p n="7">7. But eſpecially let not thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe intrench upon that veneration, which is always due to the Divine Being, his Attributes, Ordinances and Words: for as it argues a great profaneneſs, not to dread <hi>him that ought to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> who ſhakes not the earth onely, but alſo heaven: ſo can it be never ſafe to play with ſuch edge-tools, as cannot be unwiſely uſed without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; or make a jeſting buſineſs of that, for which God hath ſaid he will in no wiſe hold a man guiltleſs. And ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:42531:33"/>it is a ſtrange impiety our days are grown to, whereby not onely as formerly, men make a ſport of jeering Godlineſs, but they make no ſpare of jeering God himſelf; and ſeem to know the Scriptures for no other end, but to uſe them as Tennis-balls for recreation. But if <hi>God be in heaven, and thou upon the earth,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould <hi>thy words be few,</hi> there's a greater reaſon that they ſhould be reverend.</p>
            <p>My next advice ſhould be for the choice of your Recreations, wherein perhaps you may think advice is not ſo pertinent; becauſe <hi>trahit ſua quem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> voluptas,</hi> and every man chuſes recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as he is inclin'd; yet, I ſuppoſe, 'tis not amiſs to deſire, that here, you ſhould love with diſcretion, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect your thoughts that way, from whence may (if not the moſt of emolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) yet certainly the leaſt of damage enſue. That you ſhould not make your recreation your buſineſs, nor (as one quibled not unwittily) your va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation your vocation, I need not admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh. Neceſſity hath impos'd that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:42531:34"/>law upon you, <hi>to work or not eat.</hi> You being, I hope, of too much ſpirit to play the paraſite, and pitch up toyls to catch Dear in a platter: But were it not ſo, I ſhould abhor the thought of your living uſeleſly; and be like a Spunge, which breeds no moiſture, but onely is ſqueez'd out of that which it extraneouſly contracteth. And ſurely more deſpicable creatures the world bears not, then thoſe Gráſhoppers and Butterflies, which are onely imploy'd to ſing away their time, and buz about in the warm Sunſhine.</p>
            <p>Therefore in general, ſuch recreation is to be choſen, as may relax, or unbend the minde or body from their too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent devoires, not ſuch as may retund and weary them. For which cauſe, as I always thought, that they would give a pitiful account of their time ſpent, who ſit up till midnight at Cards and Dice: So had I never any fancie to thoſe recreations, which as they exerciſe not the body, ſo they rather diſturb, then relax the minde. Beſides the provocation to paſſion and vain ſpeaking, whereby we highly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe God, while we deſigne to pleaſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:42531:34"/>our ſelves. Without doubt thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations are beſt, which mix plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and profit together.</p>
            <p>For which cauſe, the reading of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory or Geography, are not of the leaſt note, and proper for thoſe whoſe trade (as yours) being for ſtanding and motion of the body, have a meet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxation in the ſedentary poſture of reading. Beſides the delight which the minde may take in the account of paſſed times, or the diſcovery of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Lands, and enjoy with eaſe and quiet the diſcoveries which others have made with care and travail, and manifold hazards: Whereby you will not onely reap a greater delight, then thoſe that go to viſit curious Structures, or beautified Gardens; but alſo attain ſo great accompliſhment, as may render you acceptable to all ingenious perſons; compleating not onely your own knowledge in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the world and forreign parts, but alſo enabling you to diſcourſe with thoſe, who at their great coſts, have been ocular ſpectators of remote Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions. And moreover (which is not a ſmall advantage) you will be furniſhed
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:42531:35"/>with ſuch a ſtock of examples, of the ſucceſſes which good and bad have had before you, as may be not of a little conduct to you in your own affairs; and as lights on a rocky ſhore, be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to prevent your ſhip wrack.</p>
            <p>And further too, you will not be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by this kinde of divertiſement from being at hand, to attend upon ſuch occurrents as may accidently preſent themſelves: for he verily was not out, whoſe Proverb was, <hi>Keep thy ſhop, and thy ſhop will keep thee.</hi> Attendance to him that drives a Trade, being as neceſſary to thriving, as the eye of a Maſter to make an Horſe fat; not onely preventing thereby the miſhaps, which many times befal through ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; but alſo being ready to take occaſion by the forelock, and make uſe of any thing which comes to your advantage: which if you're out of the way, goes to another place, and never inquires after you any further; meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſuch things as quite juſtle out all thoſe thoughts which they had of you. It is therefore very expedient (like a ſhort bowl) to lye in the way,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:42531:35"/>and in likelihood to be knockt up neerer the Miſtreſs.</p>
            <p>But if this be lookt upon as too me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy and reſtrain'd, and you ſeem to need more of motion, and a freer Air; to walk with ſome friend in the open Air, is a pleaſurable and healthful recreation; when you have not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the pleaſure of diſcourſe to delight the minde, but alſo the agitation of the walk, to exerciſe the body: For the way which ſome delight in, when buſineſs is over, to ſit and tope at a Club, is like the hanging of a Blote-Herring in the ſmoke, when a cloſe room, and the ſteam of Tobacco, muſt needs be as conducing to health, as <hi>Lincolnſhire</hi>-Fens are expedient to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent an Ague.</p>
            <p>The Dancing and the Fencing-School (the recreations of ſome) are both ſubject to alike inconvenience in this, that they draw to company (for the moſt part) not commendable; and the refunding of ſuch conventions, is (for the moſt part) into a Tavern; Such company ſeldom breaking up, without a parting cup. But they have beſides too, their particular evils. The
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:42531:36"/>firſt inducing thee to ſhew thine abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties among the Ladies; where, if not advis'd, thou art drawn in, beyond a retreat; or at leaſt, to frisk away much of thy time and eſtate. The other expoſing thee to ſuch conteſts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, while it pretends to enable thee, thou art often left in the lurch; thy skill being beaten out of the field by a reſolute fool-hardineſs, and thine art (uſed to conflict with art) findes it ſelf oppoſed with that courage and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which with unlearned blows deſignes not ſo much its own defence, as thy ruine. So that not a few more, taught in the art of Fencing, have miſcarried, ingaging upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of their skill, then ever were by that their skill defended.</p>
            <p>But the great divertiſement of the preſent age, is the frequenting of Plays; which in the practice of it among us, doubleſs is very vitious, where the deſigne is laid, rather to corrupt youth, then to inform it; and matter is ſo apparelled, as ſeems rather to irritate luſt, then to ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> it: Perſons gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally coming from thence, not often
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:42531:36"/>much the wiſer, very often much the viler.</p>
            <p>The courting of Ladies is a pleaſant (indeed) and gentile divertiſement; ſo I call it; for he is mad that makes it his buſineſs, or thinks it worth his while, to ſet a ſeal upon a bubble: yet I muſt tell you, it is accompanyed with not a few, nor ſmall inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: for you can hardly be fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick enough in your attire, to ſuit their fancie; nor your diſcourſe vain enough to fit their humour: for though ſome few of them will Philoſophize, the generality of them are ſo futile, that you have little cauſe to wonder the Poets imagin'd <hi>Venus concreta ſpumâ.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, for the expence, a Coach and ſix Horſes is not more coſtly; for he that courts a Lady without gifts, calls an Hawk without a Lure; which they are free to receive, not to requite; looking upon what you give, not as the effect of your bounty, but their merit; and that you are richly reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſome kinder ſneer, or more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable compliance.</p>
            <p>But alſo, a Treat is as neceſſary an Appendix of this practice, as a good
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:42531:37"/>Log for <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> which they value meerly by its coſt; wherein to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, is eſteemed baſe; and you are dirty, if you examine how you are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly cheated.</p>
            <p>Moreover, this practice is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out its danger: for if it be a beauty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der covert, 'tis impoſſible to act your love ſo Platonically, as not to give of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to the yellow ſtockens; and then remember, <hi>Jealouſie is the rage of a man;</hi> and if it be poſſible to know when it began, you ſhall never know when 'twill end.</p>
            <p>If it be an aſſociated beauty which you wait upon, you are ſure to finde that ſtock dear to buy, becauſe 'tis vy'd for. And they have the art to raiſe the commodity, by the conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the bidders: So that there's nothing to be had there, but what's inhanc'd. Beſides, in this you're cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain either to quarrel with your Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals for the feather of her fancie in dangerous conteſts, or be reflected up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (if you are wiſer) as cowardly, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generous.</p>
            <p>If it be a ſolitary beauty you court, which as yet is <hi>intemerata virgo;</hi> ſo
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:42531:37"/>that none beſides take to the ſent; ſhe will not long be ſo: for your atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance will be but like the Fowlers Stale, the appearance of which, brings but others to the net. And therefore they delight to have ſuch an one ſhew'd, and how related; which though it may be you are ſhy of, and would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy yours by your ſelf, yet they hate this kinde of privacy, thinking that ware judg'd marketable, that hath ſtore of cuſtomers. But beſides, though your intentions perhaps are general, yet the facile woman thinks you have a particular affection, and judges that while you but court her as a Miſtreſs, you woe her as a wife; and ſo is apt, either to engage her own affection beyond the reach of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable retreat, or hath thence confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence enough to challenge you with thoſe promiſes and obligations, which your frolick tongue might be free to utter, but you not free to make good. And which is worſe, the world is apt to impoſe upon you too, and either judge you vain, to level at that mark which you intended not to hit; or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious, to deſert thoſe colours for want
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:42531:38"/>of Pay, under which you liſted your ſelf as a Volunteer. But this is not all; for fair faces, and taking behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, are apt to enkindle irregular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and engage the fancie in thoſe amorous Flames, which if thoſe you treat are too honourable and chaſte to comply with, you may be induc'd to quench in the <hi>Barathrum</hi> of a common ſewer; and then into how deep a Ditch you plunge your ſelf, <hi>Solomon</hi> will tell you; whence we muſt not expect you to emerge, but with a carbonadoed body, and decocted eſtate; which God forbid.</p>
            <p>But of all Recreations, there's none more healthful or more delightful, then to ride abroad on a good horſe; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you have not onely the freſh Air, and the delightful proſpect of pleaſant Fields, variated as you make your jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; but your body is exerciſed without its own labour, and the ſpirits actuated without wearineſs. An Horſe being a creature deſtinated by the Divine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment for the eaſe and delight of man: Of that Air and generous ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that while his loftineſs ſcorns ſervitude, he yet ſeems to take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to do ſervice to you, and acts not
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:42531:38"/>out of a forreign compulſion, but an innate metal, being for eaſe and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and therein going beyond that of gay apparel.</p>
            <p>But to buy an Horſe, and not be able to judge of him; or to keep an Horſe, and not be acquainted with his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, whether he be well or ill, duly ordered, or otherwiſe; is the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to be abus'd, and to make a vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of your pleaſure: For in putting off an Horſe, men commonly uſe the largeſt conſciences; and thoſe which will ſcruple at the Tithing of Aniſe and Cummin otherwiſe, will in this caſe make no bones of a Sirloyn of Beef. 'Tis therefore beſt to buy, not upon report, but your own judgement; which you may eaſily attain by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and the comparing of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound Horſe with a ſound one; having a curious eye, that letteth paſs not any thing without note, from the lip to the very heels, bringing every part to a ſtrict examination. And be adviſed never to buy an Horſe which you ſee hath a fault; for 'tis a chance (when you have bought him) if he have not faults which you did not ſee.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:42531:39"/>
            <p>In the experience which I have had in this kinde, I have obſerved, that it is better to buy an Horſe that is fat, then otherwiſe; becauſe then you may be ſure good meat will make him ſo, which 'twill never do with ſome: and 'tis to be ſuppos'd, that no man will bring his Horſe to market out of fleſh, if a ſmall matter will make him ſo: Moreover, ſtore of fleſh is an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that that Horſe hath not been ſurfeited; or if he hath, that it is well worn out.</p>
            <p>I have further taken notice, that it is not good to buy an Horſe that hath any diſparity in his ſhape, as, long poſtern'd, inward knee'd, narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waſted; becauſe the principal excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie in an Horſe, being his ſtrength and nimbleneſs; what may render him defective in theſe, makes him ſo much uſeleſs.</p>
            <p>'Tis alſo beſt, not to lay out money upon an Horſe that hath not good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. For that being the end, for which commonly men buy, that they may be accommodated in their eaſie carriage, you will finde that Horſe hard to put off, which hath not this to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:42531:39"/>recommend him. 'Tis therefore very good always before you buy, to feel the Horſes going under you; for you thereby may not onely beſt judge of his pace and mettle, but alſo diſcover any lameneſs or imperfection, which he would not diſcover when manag'd by a Rider, who endeavours its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealment: For which cauſe alſo, 'tis very expedient to run an Horſe in hand upon the ſtones or ſome hard gound while another rides him; for the Horſe having his tread free, to make his complaint with it, and preſt with the weight of the Rider, will diſcover any foundring, ſtrain, or old infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which otherwiſe he would make no ſhew of. But this diſcourſe may be more ſeaſonable many years hence, if it ſhall pleaſe God ſo to bleſs your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as that you may bear the charge of ſuch a convenience: For an Horſe is a great eater, and will not be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained without a very conſiderable coſt; which no wiſe agrees with him, that hath not a purſe proportionable to bear it. Indeed, when <hi>out of the eater comes forth meat,</hi> and an Horſe is for profit, as well as convenience, the caſe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:42531:40"/>is altered; but this ſeldom happens to thoſe in the City. And as ſeldom is it, if ever, that thoſe who are not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fluſh men, and keep houſe in Town, do not therewith ride their Eſtates off their legs, and bring themſelves to a ſpeedie ruine.</p>
            <p>As to what concerns your converſe with men, let it be your choice to deal with thoſe which are honeſt; which yet ſo deal with, as to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the miſchief, if they ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you, and prove to be Knaves. For as there are many, to whom conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their duty is as forcible as an hundred obligations to binde them to do uprightly; ſo are there not a few, who make pretended ſincerity, as a cloak to cover their deceit, and make it their buſineſs to fiſh with that bait; whom to diſcern is as diſſicult, as the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Philoſophers Stone; and you will be never taught it, but by dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bought experience.</p>
            <p>But be moſt cautious of thoſe that ſpeak the faireſt, eſpecially if that be ſubitane, or extraordinary: for though it be a common way to give pills in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:42531:40"/>pap, and adminiſter that which is bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wrapt up in ſweet-meat; yet this is ſo natural, that it is ſtill in uſe; and ſtratagems are all in general thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd, though diverſifyed in mode and figure. And what he ſaid by his own experience ſo many years ago, <hi>Tuta frequenſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> via eſt, per amici fallere nomen;</hi> you may meet with five hundred, who can by their own experience tell you the ſame ſtill.</p>
            <p>But then be wary to conceal your ſuſpitions, leſt of a dubious friend you make a doubtleſs enemy; and he that before onely intended to ſerve his own ends of you, now deſignes to vent his malice too.</p>
            <p>Yet however, do not profeſs animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities with any man: for beſides that it is moſt unchriſtian to keep anger over-night; and we have no other promiſe of being forgiven of God, then as we forgive one another; it is doubtleſs very imprudent: For there is no creature ſo inconſiderable, which may not finde an opportunity to vent its ſpite, with thy miſchief; which God hath admoniſhed us of, in that he
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:42531:41"/>hath made the Elephant, the biggeſt of Beaſts, obnoxious to the Mouſe, the leaſt of them; by whoſe running up his Trunk, he is more plagued, then by any of his ſtouteſt adverſaries. And ſtory tells of the moſt valiant Kings, who have fallen by the hand of the meaneſt Raſcals: and I remember I read of a Turkiſh Viſier ſlain in the very <hi>Divan</hi> by a Gregarian Souldier, whom he had many years before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, who by a long perplext con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance, had from that very time laid a train for the execution of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge; which he reſolved to effect, though certain to periſh in the adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Therefore if any diſputes or offences do occur, which it is hard al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to avoid; let them be acted with as little paſſion as may be; that the concerned perſon may plainly ſee, that the conteſt was not the effect of thine envie, but intereſt; and then too, let thy next congreſſion be with as ſerene a look as may be: For as we uſe to ſay; <hi>The ſecond blow makes the fray;</hi> ſo the next meeting either makes up a quarrel, or perpetuates it.</p>
            <p>But on the other hand, be ready to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:42531:41"/>oblige all with real kindneſſes, at leaſt kinde words: For, as <hi>William</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>That man is little worth, who is not worth a ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation:</hi> So may we ſay, That man is of little remark, who is not worth a few fair words, that coſt nothing. And verily, this kinde of affability and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficious reſpect to men, conduceth not a little to attract their good opinion: And the contrary diſguſteth thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, who are not unwiſe men; and cauſeth them to ſet a note of diſlike upon thoſe, who have paſſed by them without that acknowledgement of reſpect, which they conceived due to themſelves.</p>
            <p>You ſhall moreover finde a principal way of obliging others to conſiſt in the art of conferring courteſies hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely; ſo to beſtow them, as that they may have the beſt ſide turn'd out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and be made moſt acceptable. In which reſpect 'tis beſt to antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate the expectation of the receiver, and do before you're askt: For there are many modeſt tempers, that ſtrain ſo much upon their own inclinations to intreat a kindeneſs, that they think
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:42531:42"/>in ſo doing they have dearly bought it. But if you are requeſted, what you intend to do, delay not; for <hi>hope de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred makes the heart ſad;</hi> and 'twas <hi>Seneca</hi>'s obſervation, <hi>Qui cito dat, his dat.</hi> But if thou art askt, and muſt deny, let the party ſee 'twas not out of choice, but neceſſity; and hand it to him with ſuch ſoft words, as may even oblige him, in the handſomneſs of the repulſe.</p>
            <p>Yet in this, and indeed in all other affairs, the tempers of thoſe perſons you deal with muſt be carefully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd: for many ſpirits are like gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velly Land, whoſe heat and barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is ſuch, as never requites the charge beſtow'd on it. You will therefore generally finde courteſies thrown away upon perſons that are proud or cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous: the one being of that fondneſs, as to think all but his own deſert; the other of that baſeneſs, as to ſet a very low value upon the higheſt merit. To do a benefit therefore for ſuch as theſe, that will be coſtly to you, with hope of requital, proves like mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and pains expended in the queſt of the Philoſophers ſtone; which hath
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:42531:42"/>hitherto evaporated in ſmoak and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration.</p>
            <p>You may hence obſerve, that the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying of the diſpoſitions of men, is of great uſe; not onely in what I have ſaid, but alſo in the management of all affairs: For it is much more eaſie to act a deſigne upon a man, to which he is naturally inclin'd, then otherwiſe. Therefore he that intends to bring a covetous man to act liberally, may as well expect to make a Water Spaniel of a Sheep, or good meat of a Whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone. 'Tis beſt then to make uſe of ſuch in the chanel wherein they run; and thoſe commonly are free of their words, who are cloſe of their coyn; and will be ready to do you any kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs wherein they may ſpeak for you, when they had rather part from their blouds, then let you have a penny of their money. And if you expect that ſuch as theſe ſhould do handſomely, when in the fag-end of a bargain you leave a piece of Plate, or ſuchlike gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity to their diſpoſition; you are as certainly diſappointed, as if you ſhould look that a dogs tail ſhould afford you frankincenſe. And verily that ſtory
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:42531:43"/>is here worth the remembring, of the Juſtices Clerk ſent by his Maſter to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent an whole Boar to him, who lately dyed worth ſo many thouſands, got by ſaving. The young man gives a Porter eighteen pence to bear it thither, big with expectation that the gratuity would be proportionate to ſo fair a preſent; which having preſented with ſuch words as were likely to give it the beſt acceptance, the rich Chuff draws his purſe, and after a long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble of good counſel, that he ſhould be a provident husband of what was in this kinde beſtow'd upon him, gives him twopence: and as the man was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited, ſo was the Maſter.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, 'tis no ſinall prudence to make choice of ſuch, if you are concern'd in an Arbitration wherein matter of money may be in controverſie: for thoſe of a free ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with eaſe part from ſuch ſums as not much, which your cloſe Sirs would ſtrain at like a Camel.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe 'tis very expedient to be skill'd in Phyſiognomy; I mean the art of diſcovering the tempers of perſons by their looks: from whence
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:42531:43"/>no doubt there is a more exact diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very to be made, then by any relations or reports whatſoever: and for my own part (I may ſay) I have been in this reſpect the leaſt deceived: For though it be poſſible for men to cover their paſſions, and conceal their croſs diſpoſitions from any betray their words may make of them, till they are ready to act; yet it is not poſſible for them to obliterate thoſe Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of Nature, whereby 'tis not hard to read them without their leave. And though it ſometimes falls out, that by cuſtom and vice; men are not (ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times) what Nature made them; yet that alteration is made by ſuch habits, as leave a ſufficient mark of themſelves behinde, and make the diſcovery rather more eaſie then difficult. The attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Art is not ſo eaſie by any documents whereby you may be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, as by your own private obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the comparing of the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of mens actions, with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer judgement which you paſſed on their looks; or <hi>à poſteriore</hi> comparing your apprehenſions of their preſent looks, with what you know of their
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:42531:44"/>paſſed actions; which transfer as a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to your conceipt on all parallel Phyfiognomies.</p>
            <p>Neither will you finde it leſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to diſcover mens preſent thoughts by their preſent looks, then their inclinations by their features: For if he that carped at the form of man, found fault onely in this, that he wanted a window in his heart; Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath ſomething clear'd her ſelf in that, for that <hi>Vultus eſt indicium quid vultis:</hi> diſcovering (do what we can) in ſudden appearances, thoſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of our minde, which we would ſhould be for ever conceal'd; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly we diſcover them ſo much the more, in being vext that we cannot but diſcover them. To do which, there muſt be a quick application of the eye, to the looks of him whoſe ſentiments you would diſcover, at that very time when you think he is pincht; that you may judge by the face which he makes, whether it wrings him or no. There is alſo much of diſcovery to be made of the reſentments of others by their ſudden ſpeeches, which even from very diſcreet perſons ſometimes
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:42531:44"/>bluſter forth, and are not examined by the Court of guard; and then eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, when paſſions are up, or affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons violent. 'Tis therefore the part of a wiſe man, to be a diligent obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of every word that paſſes, though with as little obſervation from others as may be, that you do obſerve: For all ſuch ſuſpition begets caution; and <hi>in vain is the net laid in the ſight of the bird.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here on the other hand, 'tis of great uſe to conceal your own reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not to winch when you are toucht to the quick; but to diſſemble your ſenſe, till you have a due oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to diſcover it to your advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. For it very often is, that we ſpoil our affairs by diſcloſing them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are hatcht; and turning them out into the world (as ripe for execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) which have ſtill need of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundine of further advice and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. For which cauſe, as time is the firſt of all things, ſo is it the principal too; it being almoſt impoſſible to do any thing well, that is not done timely.</p>
            <p>Neither is it leſs uſeful, many times,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:42531:45"/>to cover altogether our apprehenſions, and ſeem to take no notice of thoſe things, which indeed do give us juſt cauſe of regret; eſpecially too, when thoſe we are to deal with, are either too mighty for us, or we expect may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to us. Upon which account, I remember I have read of <hi>Coſmus,</hi> that it was not the leaſt thing conducing to the inurement of his infant-dominion, that he had the art of diſſembling the inſults of the Spaniſh pride, and the envie of his ſuſpitious Neighbours. And therefore thoſe forward tongues, or peeviſh tempers, which fling as ſoon as toucht; and make it more to vent their preſent heats, then conſult their future conveniences; Not onely create to themſelves many troubles, but alſo pull off the hair of thoſe oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, which otherwiſe in due time might have fairly preſented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>Yet on the other ſide, there is no greater <hi>remora</hi> to mens affairs, then that delatory ſlowneſs, which, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the fair gale of opportunity blows, yet love to put off till to morrow; and then ſet out like a Coach and ſix
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:42531:45"/>Horſes, with ſuch tedious preparation, that before all things are ready, the Game's ſtarted to their hand, and they come juſt the day after the fair; when with an irkſom difficulty they are put to't to retreive thoſe things, which but a while ago flew fair before them.</p>
            <p>And here you may take notice, that in the uſe of men, 'tis of huge advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to obſerve the time: for there is not that man to be found, whoſe temper is ſo even, as not to expoſe him ſometimes more waxy for impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, then at other times. And if it were not ſo, the very contingencies that happen, do differently diſpoſe us: For which cauſe we are more inclin'd to be free to others, when a proſperous gale hath breathed upon us; and are ready then to give a crabbed anſwer, when ſome peeviſh occaſion before hath angred us. And the <hi>Craſis</hi> of men, as it is very divers; ſo are they more or leſs complying, as the preſent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant humour is accidentally ſedated, or made ſharper. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as cholerick perſons are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly peeviſh till they have din'd, that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:42531:46"/>the ſtomack have ſomething in't, to imploy the active humour; ſo are thoſe that are flegmatick, or melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, rarely free, or debonair, till their more ponderous and dull ingredients are warm'd and made more active by the adventitious heat, which wine, or ſome ſtrong liquor contributeth; or their ſpirits awakened by ſome ſuch pleaſant company or diſcourſe, as may leave ſome tang behinde it. And therefore choice of time will as much difference the ſucceſs of your applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which you make to perſons, as wind and tide with or againſt, ſhall ſpeed or retard a paſſage.</p>
            <p>And for this very cauſe, in ſuch caſes, 'tis not ground enough to give up your hopes as deſperate, becauſe you ſucceeded not at the firſt; for a ſecond or third time may finde the humour better diſpos'd to receive the impreſſions which you intended.</p>
            <p>But however, be always adviſed ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to reſiſt one humour with the like: For it is excellently advantagious when paſſion is up, to look on, and with a ſedated minde to obſerve the indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreet paſſages which then occur, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:42531:46"/>every perſon lays himſelf open at ſuch a rate, as renders him not a little obnoxious to the retorts of him, that with a compoſed ſpirit takes notice of them. And that this is ſo, is eaſily diſcovered, if you reflect, when you are return'd to your own bent, upon that exorbitance and indiſcretion, which in thoſe wilde fits you flew out into. For which cauſe, to oppoſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with paſſion, ſeldom produceth other effect then a too-late repentance for both. And 'twill be found abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly better to put on your Mittens, and handle the paſſionate with as much ſoftneſs as may be. And I have known men of that tune, whom in the fit you'd have thought irrefragable, plan'd by this means to as much ſmoothneſs, as could reaſonably be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. And whereas if in ſnuff and diſtaſte you may fling away from ſuch <hi>re infecta;</hi> a little patience and good words may do your buſineſs, and ſend you away with what you come for.</p>
            <p>But take this as a general caution, to deal as little as may be with thoſe over topping men, to whom a man
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:42531:47"/>cannot with confidence come and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his own. Upon which account I'll tell you a publick ſtory, of which you may make a private application. It was diſputed in the days of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> in a Parliament then holden, whether if the Queen ſhould have a Childe, the Tutelage of it, and ſome places of ſtrength, ſhould be put in King <hi>Philips</hi> hand; the King of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering his Bond, faithfully to deliver up his truſt, if the Childe ſhould dye. And the greater number of the Houſe inclining to the affirmative, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding that ſo great a Kings Bond was an ample ſecurity; the Lord <hi>Paget</hi> ſtands up, and demands, if the King ſhould refuſe to do as he is bound, upon the death of the Childe, who ſhall put his Bond in ſuit, and where? which demand was ſo difficult to finde an anſwer, that the buſineſs fell without more ado.</p>
            <p>And 'tis much one, to have dealings with thoſe, who have ſo great an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence on our affairs, that we muſt be content with what meaſure they'll give us: for to knock off, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, if we like not our matters, is
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:42531:47"/>the loſs of our friend, and a greater advantage.</p>
            <p>Be alſo adviſed in all dealings of importance, to manage them by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and not by Meſſage; which do ſo frequently forget, or miſtake, that your buſineſs is made a quite different mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then 'twas when you ſent it.</p>
            <p>But this ſhould be eſpecially ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, when ſuch anſwers are given, as you may ſuſpect may prove offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive; for ſent by the mouth of another, there may be a word put in, which may ſo inflame the ſenſe, as to make that intolerable, which out of your mouth was directed with a paſſable contrivance.</p>
            <p>And for the ſame reaſon, 'tis not good to take pet at any ſuch returns as come at ſecond-hand, when you may be deny'd in ſome eaſie requeſt: for I ſometimes have known, when an anſwer hath been brought, enough to divide the moſt intimate friends; which when 'twas inquir'd into, prov'd no more to the minde of the party that ſent it, then <hi>George a Green,</hi> to the man in the Moon.</p>
            <p>And you'll finde it as falſe to judge
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:42531:48"/>by report, when the actions of men come under diſpute: For the miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of men, not ſeldom diſtort and wring that out of joynt to make it moſt monſtrous, when the party that did it was candid in his thoughts. And the prejudice of men adds ſo much to this ſcore, that they will have often a bunch for an horn: and the matter is not much, there, to finde a knot, where 'tis before-hand reſolv'd to finde it or make it. Therefore, as in matters of news, I have always ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to make ſuch an abatement, as may bear a proportion with the facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the relater; ſo you'll finde that as needful in the reports made of men; for you may be ſure, that <hi>ill-will doth never ſpeak well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe I ſpake before of treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Letter, you muſt be adviſed to be therein very wary, becauſe there is your hand as a witneſs againſt you; ſo that as to matter of weight, which may produce ſuit, 'tis not amiſs to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what is ſaid of <hi>Tiberius Caeſar,</hi> That ſome of his Letters to the Senate were <hi>ex conſulto ambiguae</hi> ſuch as he intended ſhould be interpreted, not
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:42531:48"/>according to the plain words, but the concernments of thoſe whom he had to deal with: For ſuch words may be found out, and ſo plac'd, as ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to a promiſe in the apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Reader, who is conſcious of the matter you treat of, which will not be ſo conſtrued in the judgement of thoſe who may come to take cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of the matter in queſtion.</p>
            <p>If God ſhall ſo bleſs you, as that you live to ſerve out your time, with ſuch approbation of induſtry and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs as ſhall manumit you with a good report; 'twill not be amiſs to have by you ſome general advice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning your ſetting up, becauſe God knoweth whether I ſhall then be alive to judge of thoſe particular concerns, which may induce or diſſwade it.</p>
            <p>What I have therefore here firſt to adviſe you of, is, that you look upon this buſineſs, as that which deſerves much advice. There being not a few, who by their haſte, and precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in this affair, have ruined their fortunes; and while they have been weary of being ſervants, have made
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:42531:49"/>themſelves in a ſhort time perpetual ſlaves to indigence and want. For if having once ſet up, you then miſcarry, it proves like the blaſting of a young ſprout, which, if not thereby utterly kill'd, yet becomes ſo checkt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, that it never attains a freſh and flouriſhing condition after. It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you therefore to look before you leap, and not to be induc'd by the name of Maſter and a Shop, to skip into that in haſte, from whence you will be ſhortly turn'd out with ſhame.</p>
            <p>It hath been obſerv'd, that they ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom prove well, who ſet up young; that age being for the moſt part preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitate, and forwarder to do then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, and alſo apt to pre-occupy the ſucceſs of things, by a too promiſing hope; and like young Setters, to ſet an Haunt inſtead of a Covie; whereby they are many times groſly abuſed, and erre at ſuch a rate, as admits of (onely, if any, yet) a difficult recovery. Whereas thoſe that like Bobbed Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridges have been ruſt in the net of deception, by what they have obſerv'd at others charge, are much more wary,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:42531:49"/>and cautelous of being again trapan'd. Beſides, age doth give a natural allay, like a <hi>Bartholomew</hi>-dew, cooling the immoderate heat and raſhneſs of youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger years.</p>
            <p>It is therefore taken notice of, that young men do then proſper beſt, when they have either ſerved as Journey-men unto ſome wary Stagers; or have the happineſs to be taken in as partners un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch. Whereby, as Bears by their grown Cubs, they are taught to catch the prey with the greateſt cleverneſs and certainty, and with the leaſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard.</p>
            <p>'Tis not amiſs here alſo to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh you, that great Rents have very often broke the back of young begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; who before they could get ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, and gain cuſtom to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fray the charge of ſo great expence, are drain'd dry, to the very vital bloud, and expire like a Candle for want of fat to feed the fire on't. Conſider therefore, that <hi>omne principium eſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile;</hi> and 'tis wiſdom to diſpoſe all thy projects in a proportion to that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity: For he that arms himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his own dimenſions, is incumbred
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:42531:50"/>with his own Furniture, and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falls the more ridiculous ſubject of others ſcorne and triumph. Be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore adviſed to begin warily, having as the firſt, ſo the laſt game to play; and as one jeſted, it being all one, and one all; it concerns you ſo to diſpoſe it, as may admit of the leaſt hazard.</p>
            <p>Nor is it leſs good counſel, to begin low, according to the advice of the Country-man, to eat your brown Bread firſt: If there were no other reaſon, at leaſt, becauſe 'tis ſhameful to come lower. And experience tells us, that that Bullock which hath been fed with Hay, will almoſt ſtarve before 'twill be kept with Straw: for though there be nothing more eaſie then to come down, ſo there's nothing more difficult then to bring our mindes to it.</p>
            <p>But further, as thoſe Structures which are raiſed higheſt, have always their foundations laid loweſt; ſo you can hardly inſtance in any great eſtate, whoſe beginning was not with ſuch a providence, as conſulted for mean things. And this doubtleſs may be rendred as the principal cauſe, that ſo very few of thoſe prove ſucceſsful,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:42531:50"/>who have been furniſh'd out into the world plentifully, by their friends: For building thereupon with too much confidence, they ſet out at ſuch a rate, as before they have run far, breaks their wind: whereas they who come forth under-hatcht, conſcious of their own infirmity, ride with a ſtrait hand; and if they are wiſe, put not into a gallop, till their wind be well rackt; and by that means prove of good ſpur-met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the laſt.</p>
            <p>And now let me tell you, there's no one thing deſerves the care of a young beginner more then his ſervants; who, if they be beaten to the world, and know how to do any thing, they're cunning enough to abuſe and cheat you: Their opportunities too being ſuch as are hard to avoid. Let me therefore in this particular give you ſomething of advice.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be ſure never to truſt any of them that have a colloguing, fawning way: For they are perſons whom nature hath, as it were, cut out for deceit, and not onely fitted with habiliaments, but alſo a natural promptneſs thereto:
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:42531:51"/>and if I may tell you mine own experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, I remember not that I ever had to do with any of them, which proved otherwiſe. And they are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally of that impudence, that like thoſe at Cape <hi>Bon Speranz,</hi> they'll pick your pocket, and look in your face; pretending always moſt, what they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend leaſt. And therefor there is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecial need of your caution in thoſe very things, which they profeſs moſt againſt; they being generally like her, who made the world believe ſhe could endure no Eggs, till it was found that her uſual breakfaſt was a groats<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Never make your ſelf over-fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar with your ſervants, nor take them for your play-fellows; for familiarity begets contempt, and contempt breaks the neck of obedience: It being very rare that thoſe ſervants are ready to do, that are not kept in aw; but will be rather diſputing your commands then doing them; which beware that you admit not: It being better in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſpects, to erre in commanding what is not convenient, then to amend it upon the advice of an ordinary ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:42531:51"/>they being incouraged by ſuch a condeſcenſion, to argue with you the expediencie of your commands e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver after, and upon that account to uſe ſuch language, as is not to be indured; which to remedy, when got an head, you'll be neceſſitated to uſe ſuch ſharp corroſives, as may againſt your minde, if for your turn, part you and your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Never acquaint a ſervant with that ſecret which may be to your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice if reveal'd: For when once you ſtand upon their courteſie, they then grow inſolent, and make no bones to retract their ſervice, when they know you dare not exact it. Beſide, how baſe a ſervitude is it to have our noſes held to the Grind-ſtone by thoſe, which we know are bound to obey us? and ſo to ſtand in fear of their diſcovery, that however abus'd, we muſt be mealy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth'd.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Expect not to oblige an ordinary ſervant by your kindneſſes. For I could never ſee any of them, but were like thoſe <hi>fera animalia,</hi> which upon every diſtaſte return to their natural ferity, and forget all bonds of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:42531:52"/>they received from you. Beſides, they have a general comment, whereby they interpret all your favours; which they judge to be the effect, not of your goodneſs, but their own deſert; and conclude, that you are therefore kinde to them, becauſe you cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them; which conception having once imagined, they grow as touchy as Waſps, and upon every ruffle bid you provide your ſelf.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Be not in a ſervants debt, if you can make any ſhiſt to come out of it: For they look upon the forbearance of their mony, as ſo great a kindneſs, which if you take not care to requite, they'll take care to do it themſelves; and aſſure your ſelf, 'tis no good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry in any thing to let them be their own Carvers. And which is worſe, they take occaſion thence to grow refractory, and inſult; which by all expedients ſhould be avoided, in a Country where Laws are ſo little ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in this reſpect, and wherein what they are, 'tis dedecorous to uſe them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Let your behaviour to your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants be with a general equanimity,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:42531:52"/>and even temper; not finding fault through the peeviſhneſs of your own humour, but the juſtneſs of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merit: For no one thing doth more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair authority, and abate a readineſs to amend thoſe things for which they are increpated, then when 'tis obſerv'd, we are of ſuch a temper, as we call <hi>in Dock out Nottle:</hi> ſometimes <hi>ſtumbling at a ſtraw, and</hi> another time <hi>leaping over a block.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Let your ſervants be ſupplyed in all things meet for them, in ſickneſs and in health: For all ſuch things are what they bargain for. And 'tis great iniquity to require ſervice from them, while you give not what you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted for, to them. And truely in this caſe 'tis better rather to exceed then otherwiſe, if it be done with due providence and caution: For it is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily baſe, that the world ſhould ſay, we increaſed our wealth, with what ſhould have been put into our ſevants bellies.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Be not inclin'd to an Eveſdrop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and underhand hearkning what your ſervants ſay in their privacies: For it is rare (even though they love you)
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:42531:53"/>but at one time or other you ſhall hear them curſe you. And at ſuch times, I have obſerv'd, they are apt to prat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle that which they never mean, and pleaſe themſelves in a way of ſpeaking freely, <hi>as the Collier that call'd my Lord Mayor knave, when he was got upon</hi> Briſtow-<hi>cauſey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. Obſerve that due <hi>decorum</hi> which our Laws require, not to turn away a ſervant without a quarters warning, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in ſuch caſes wherein 'tis perilous to keep them: it being indeed very unjuſt, that thoſe whoſe livelihoods depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on imployment, ſhould at your pleaſure be expoſed to want, without ſuch fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, as that they may provide for themſelves. And 'twill alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn you of ſuch raſhneſs, as will not eaſily finde a fair excuſe: All ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currents too, as they diſaccommodate them, not failing to bring along with them their inconveniences on you.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, let your care be, that in all things your ſervants give God his due: for 'tis in vain to expect that they ſhould be juſt to you, when they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that you are careleſs whether they are ſo to God; and will never ſcruple
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:42531:53"/>to abuſe you their Maſter below, when they have liberty given them to offend thine and their Maſter above. And verily in this caſe, the danger's great, where there's a freedome given to do wickedly: For beſides that all righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is like a Golden-chain, ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon one another, that he who makes no conſcience of breaking one, may upon the ſame account break all: 'Tis juſt with God to puniſh one ſin with another, and permit thoſe to deal unrighteouſly with you, whom thou permitteſt to behave themſelves wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly to him. And moreover, 'tis not to be doubted, but as God bleſſed the houſe of <hi>Potiphar</hi> for good <hi>Joſephs</hi> ſake: ſo he hath a proportionableneſs of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance to execute upon thoſe families, where his name by any one is much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured.</p>
            <p>But now there is a different manner of acting to be exerciſed towards thoſe, who ſhall be taken by you as Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices; for their concerns are much different from thoſe of an ordinary ſervant, you being become to them <hi>loco parentis:</hi> They giving no ſmall part of their portion for your Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:42531:54"/>and expending no ſmall part of their lives in doing you ſervice; and therefore you are concern'd to own ſuch in a more then ordinary acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement. And as they to that end became your ſervants, that they might in due time become Maſters, ſo are they to be uſed in all reſpects as thoſe ſlips <hi>futurae ſpei,</hi> which juſtly exact your care and incouragement; and therefore to be managed, not tyrannized over: and ſo to be uſed, that while you drive on by them your own advantages, you remember alſo, that you are bound to promote theirs. And therefore I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but congratulate the integrity of thoſe, whom I have heard rejoyce in the proſperity of thoſe who had been their Apprentices. And with as much deteſtation have I abhor'd the unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of thoſe, who by cunning pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices have blaſted the hopeful fortunes of their young ſervants; envying the thriving of ſuch as have eſcaped their hands; grudging that any Water ſhould go by their Mill, to help the Griſt of thoſe, who were ſo many years ſervants to theirs.</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:42531:54"/>
            <p>And indeed conſider, how many ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments there are to induce your ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and care, when the hopes and future joyes of a careful Father ſhall be put into your hands, to ſtand or fall at your diſcretion; who hath (it may be) drain'd himſelf beyond his abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to furniſh his ſon into your ſervice; and hath been willing to deny himſelf of his preſent conveniences, upon the account of his future hopes; which ſhall either flouriſh, or be blaſted, as your diſcretion and care ſhall be diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And verily, as we lament the fall of a Family that hath been undone <hi>à poſteriore,</hi> and mourn over the ruines of a blown-up Eſtate; ſo I think we may the more juſtly bemoan an antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated undoing, when that eſtate is nipt in the bud or flower, which if kindly and cautelouſly dealt with, might have grown to that vaſtneſs, that the Birds of the Air might have lodged under the Branches of it.</p>
            <p>And truely, who can without la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments conſider, how many hopeful Youths come up to that great City, who are miſerably expos'd to ruine, by the neglect of thoſe they are bound
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:42531:55"/>to, who being ſecur'd in their own concerns, by the ſecurity given by friends, leave the young men to run riot at their own wills, and undo them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the opportunities which they put into their hands, while they are jolly at their Country-houſes, and give them rope enough to hang them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; whereby the wretched Father is not onely diſappointed of his preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant hopes which he had conceived, but (poor heart) is involved in a debt which he never feared. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſuch as theſe, it behooves you to behave your ſelf with ſuch a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as may conduce not onely to the effecting of your own buſineſs, but alſo the promoting of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns.</p>
            <p>Your next thoughts (it may be) are concerning a Wife; and 'tis poſſible you may diſpute with your ſelf, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you ſhall marry or no; wherein to give you advice, were as pertinent as the directions of Almanack-makers, who may tell you, that in <hi>March</hi> you muſt ſow Seeds; when in that month the weather may prove ſo unkinde,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:42531:55"/>as that to ſow them in the ground, were all one as to throw them in the Kennel: many circumſtances very much altering the caſe in the expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie of wiving: Therefore what our Lord ſpeaks in this matter, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.12. he ſpeaks <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to him that is able to receive it.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the marryed life is charged with many incumbrances; and I think 'tis without diſpute, that the ſingle man (if he can ſo content himſelf) lives much the freer. But yet doubtleſs much may be ſaid on the other ſide: for the trouble of buſineſs hath a kinde of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in it: And if I may ſpeak mine own experiences, who have had in this kinde as much as moſt men; I may truely ſay, that I never was better Fleas'd, then when I had moſt to do. Buſineſs by its motion adding an heat to the ſpirits, while the unimployed, like ſtanding water, corrupt with their own idleneſs. Seceſs, through our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, not affording us ſo much oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity for Divine Contemplation, as laying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> open to the illaqueations of Satanical ſuggeſtion. Wherefore, we read <hi>David</hi> never in worſe caſe, then
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:42531:56"/>when idle on the roof of his houſe; and doubtleſs there is no good man but thinks him in better tune, when he ſaid of himſelf, <hi>that he was perſecuted as a Partridge upon the Mountains.</hi> Beſides, there is a natural tendencie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God hath inclin'd all things living to a delightful paintaking in this kinde: whence we ſee the Beaſts of the Field, but eſpecially the Fowls of the Air, denying their own conveniences, and with ſo much affection making pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for their many young ones. And if God have not indu'd us with as paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate inſtincts, 'tis becauſe we have reaſon to produce in us more powerful effects.</p>
            <p>But if we ſhould here fall into a diſcourſe, how much the diſcommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of the marryed life are compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſated with the conveniences which a good wife brings; we might poſſibly be involv'd beyond our deſigne: For not to ſpeak of that content, which is to be had in reciprocal indearments, where acts of love endeavour to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy each other, and you are attended upon ſick and well, with that affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which like Musk and Amber gives
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:42531:56"/>a moſt pleaſing acceptableneſs: what a ſatisfaction is it to have a friend, which as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of <hi>Timothy</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi>doth naturally care for our affairs?</hi> into whoſe boſome we may freely diſcharge our thoughts, and expect ſuch ſecreſie, care, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, as none elſe have a like induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to afford.</p>
            <p>If therefore ſuch thoughts as theſe ſhall prevail with you, to enter upon the marryed life; yet be advis'd not to engage therein, but with ſuch conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration as becomes a buſineſs, wherein you muſt know a very great meaſure of the contentment of your future days depends.</p>
            <p>And here let me firſt give you a cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt that abominable baſeneſs, which trapans innocent women to their utter undoing: When thoſe Citizens (which in truth have nothing) make ſhew of much, and draw in great matches, with that appearance, to the ſhame and miſery of a broken Fortune. Whereby women of good Eſtates, are not onely brought to nothing; but made worſe then nothing, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled with the incombrance and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:42531:57"/>charge of Children, for whoſe main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance there is no proviſion. And therefore I adjure you, that with a juſt abhorrencie of ſo great and ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian perfidiouſneſs, if your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours ſhould be ſo blaſted (which God forbid) that you muſt ſink, you ſink alone, rather then involve in your calamity the innocence of a Wife and Children, which ſhould be of that dear reſpect to you; and be guilty of that curſed treachery, to leave her without houſe and home, who leſt her Fathers houſe to come to yours.</p>
            <p>And for this cauſe, do not marry 'till you finde that you can ſtand on your own Legs; being in ſuch a thriving way, as with the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of Gods bleſſing, may afford an handſome ſupply for ſuch expences, as a marryed life brings with it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſuch a capacity, your thoughts may then be imployed in the care how to chuſe a good Wife; when choſen, how to obtain her; and when had, how with diſcretion to behave your ſelf to her.</p>
            <p>As for the firſt, be adviſed to chuſe ſuch for a Wife, whoſe fame is like that
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:42531:57"/>Chriſtal, which hath not ſo much as a ſand-ſpot in't, not onely in reſpect of her own Reputation, but alſo of her Relations: there being a kinde of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality in a good name, which doth over-live us, and is intail'd by the ſureſt conveyance upon our Poſterities; ſo as that there is no fine and recovery in this caſe allow'd; no time wearing out this blemiſh, nor merit ſufficient to waſh it off. Therefore it ſhould be your care, that this may run in the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt channel, where no ſoyl nor mud may defile it; but that you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, as uncontaminated from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as it ought to be your care ſo to tranſmit it unto yours. And if thoſe who breed horſes, have an eſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial caution to prevent (even thoſe onely ocular) blemiſhes which may be traduced to the Foles; it concerns us doubtleſs much more, to be wary of bringing that into our Families which may ſtick as a blemiſh into fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Generations.</p>
            <p>And upon this account, ſuch choice is to be eſchewed, as may bring an hereditary deformity or diſeaſe: For what an unkind ſight is it to ſee a mans
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:42531:58"/>houſe ſtockt with crook-backs, when the Gibbous Children ſhall repreſent the diſtorted crook-ſhoulder of their Mother, and carry always about them the publick teſtimony of your indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? For though ſome emolument might preſent its ſelf, which might induce you to make ſuch an one your bed-fellow; yet ſurely nothing ſhould prevail to take her for a breeder, and leave your name running in the winding-Chanel of a crooked defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. The like may be adviſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Hereditary diſeaſes, when the King evil, or ſuchlike which the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath, may run in the bloud of her off-ſpring; and you may ſee that fleſh rotting before its time, which you expected would have been ſome ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to your memory, when you ſhould be dead and gone.</p>
            <p>And truely upon this ſcore of our Poſterity, it is very expedient to make choice of an handſome venter: For that we ſee, that comely Mothers have, for the moſt part, as comely Children; and as rare is it, that thoſe who are not, have other Children then ſuch as are like themſelves. And though
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:42531:58"/>beauty be of its ſelf, an object fitted for our affection, being a perfection not apprehended but by a rational Creature; yet doubtleſs it is for this reaſon even prudentially eligible, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a beautiful Mother gives hopes of a fair breed; and Daughters that are handſome, are either put off with leſs portions, or to better Fortunes. And ſuch men are not a little advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taged in finding that ſuit facile, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their own comelyneſs hath been their ſpokeſman.</p>
            <p>Let your next care, which I ſhould have made the firſt, be her Religion; whereby I underſtand not onely the profeſſion of the truth, but ſuch a Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple infus'd from above, as doth diſpoſe to an holy and circumſpect converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: For as not one of theſe leaſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of the marryed life, is mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſociety; ſo doubtleſs there can be no ſuch communion, as where God himſelf makes up the third party. And the fellowſhip is not onely that of affection, whereby as <hi>Jonathan</hi> and <hi>David</hi> they become one ſoul; but that alſo, whereby they become oneſpirit, and
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:42531:59"/>are mutual helpers of one anothers faith and joy.</p>
            <p>And beſides too, there is from this Principle ſo much of inducement, not onely to bear with ſuch things, and act upon ſuch accounts, as will not be done upon any other ſcore; but alſo to avoid ſuch temptations, as morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty would ſtoop to; and to ſay as <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, How ſhall I do this great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſin againſt God!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Her diſpoſition alſo doth require your eſpecial care, being a matter not a little conducing to your peace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: For ſome perſons are of that uneven temper, that they are not one whole day friends with themſelves; and therefore when they are in the frets, will finde a Gall in a Dove, and take occaſion to quarrel at a Ball-ruſh, not becauſe it hath ſome knots in it, but becauſe it hath none; and have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to charge upon your ſcore of what they want, if not of what they ſhould have, to be ſure of what they would have. Whereas there are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers again, that nature hath allaid with an unwillingneſs to quarrel, and can hardly tell how far their patience
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:42531:59"/>can be extended; but if provokt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond that bent, they'll tear like thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and are as ſoon return'd again to as clear a Sunſhine, as gives no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance that it was fowl weather. And this ſurely is not an inconvenient temper: For whereas thoſe that are ſheepiſh, can very difficultly preſerve themſelves from being weather-born; and thoſe that are waſpiſh, are, as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>a continual dropping;</hi> and the poutiſh are like a charnel-houſe, where ſorrowful and glum ſilence make a ſolemn mourning: Theſe, like a ſmart <hi>April</hi>-ſhower, rain to make the earth look greener, and uſe frowns and tharp words, as Kings do Souldiers and hounds, onely when they are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, and in ſeaſon: Then onely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to be angry, when they lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a neceſſity of vindicating their concerns from neglect, or themſelves from contempt.</p>
            <p>And under this title of diſpoſition, we may alſo bring in her frugal incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which is not the leaſt of the feminine vertues: for all that Sex is much for outward ornament, becauſe conſcious there's not much within:
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:42531:60"/>Wherein every thing is valued not by the <hi>decet,</hi> ſo much as the <hi>conſtitit;</hi> and all is thought mean, that doth not exceed: and for you to interpoſe to moderate the expence, would be an argument of either want of affection, or a generous ſpirit. Such an one therefore whoſe natural compoſure is an allay to that extravagance, is like Mother of Pearl, which breeds its own treaſures, being very fine, and fed to as much content, with the third of that coſt, which muſt be laid out upon the ſoft back, and dainty tooth of another. And let me tell you, there is much in the educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of young women, when they have been bred up frugally, and not nurtured in that ſenſuality, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploys all thoughts, rather how to pleaſe the appetite, then appeaſe hunger; and how to be vain and gallant, then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and comely. And let me alſo tell you, there is much in the natural neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſome women, who are cut out, as it were, to make a fair ſhew with a little, and will appear very neat and handſome in that which is but ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and evince their Gentility by their gate and behaviour. Whereas, ſome
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:42531:60"/>others are like a Sow with a Saddle, on whom whatſoever coſt you beſtow, they ſhall never look otherwiſe, then like Gold in Ore, which may be rich, but is unpolliſhed; their bravery hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on, as if ſhak'd there with a fork, and they in their rich apparel look as like Gentlewomen, as a Clown in a Buff-coat and Bandeleers, doth like a Souldier. And therefore on ſuch as theſe, your expence muſt be laviſh, and coſt extream: For they know that what they wear is onely handſome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe rich; and that they are as careful in preſerving, as they are neat in wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhewing no more courteſie to a Sattin-gown, then ſome would do to a Ruſſet-coat; ſlattering out that in a few months, which would have done another credit, it may be, as many years.</p>
            <p>What is next to be thought for, is a portion, wherein as your care ſhould be wary and provident; ſo ſhould it be alſo gentile and noble: not on the one hand to take in a charge without what to maintain it; nor on the other hand, to bargain for a wiſe, as if you were higling for an Horſe in <hi>Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field:</hi>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:42531:61"/>For as prudence would teach to conſult by a good portion, for ſuch a charge as all Wives bring with them; ſo the nature of ſuch a tranſaction ſhould induce us to behave our ſelves in it, with ſuch a nobleneſs as becomes it.</p>
            <p>And in the matter of wiving, things being for the moſt part carryed on by affection, ſo in this reſpect are we chiefly concern'd to make uſe of our diſcretion: For a fair Wife without a Portion, is like a brave Houſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Furniture, where a man may pleaſe himſelf with the proſpect, but there is nothing within to keep him warm: and a Wife with a good portion, but with conditions unſuitable, is like the fat land in the <hi>Wilde,</hi> where there may be wealth, but in truth little pleaſure beſides. Therefore let a good face per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to call, good conditions to alight and enter, and a good portion put you to bed: For where wealth onely is, there will be a cold affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and where affection onely is, there will be a cold content: For as he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, <hi>ſine Cerere &amp; Baccho, friget Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus;</hi> ſo will content look pale, and love
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:42531:61"/>wax feeble, where there is not an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate to keep them plump and fair.</p>
            <p>'Tis true indeed, to marry an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endowed Wife is more diſpenſable, where there is ſuch an Eſtate as doth not need a portion: For in ſuch a caſe your love hath a greater proof, and may be ſuppos'd to lay a greater obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; and poſſibly you may expect a ſubmiſſion to your will more, and a greater compliance to your deſires. Though I muſt tell you that many in that reſpect have found themſelves mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken; no perſons being more exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant in their exceſſes, then thoſe which brought the leaſt with them. And as thoſe are commonly the proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt when preferr'd, who before were the meaneſt; ſo thoſe wives are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally the coſtlyeſt, who put leaſt into the bag to maintain it. But in truth, this whole affair depends ſo much upon the good temper and prudence of the Wife, that no other Argument; or conſideration will anſwer your deſires, if they be wanting.</p>
            <p>But be advis'd; however unendowed the woman be, let not her kindred be neceſſitous; I mean falling from what
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:42531:62"/>they had: For in confidence of your relation, they will not fail to hang upon you: and in caſe that you think it much, you'll be judged unkinde and churliſh; and the wife for their ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, muſt either prove unnatural to them, or elſe be tempted to become leſs faithful to you.</p>
            <p>But if it be your purpoſe to raiſe your Fortunes by a Wife; 'tis the firſt advice to look high enough, becauſe 'tis poſſible ſuch an application may prove; and if it do not, the diſcredit is the leſs, to be diſappointed in an arduous attempt. And however, the probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is the greater; for he that hews at a well-ſpread Oak, though his ſtrength may fail to get it down, yet is more likely to be ſupply'd, then he that onely aim'd at ſome ſimple Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>It is beſt too, to fix upon ſome grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fortune; ſuch a perſon whoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations by proſpering in their way, make a fair addition to the preſent portion; for all that comes in on free coſt: and though not to be truſted in, as no dead mens Shooes are; yet if it comes, it
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:42531:62"/>doth well; and ſo much the better, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not lookt for.</p>
            <p>And the ſame reaſon ſhould induce to marry ſuch as are akin to Land; I mean, that have not many Heirs to ſtand between them and an Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: For money is a diſpoſable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, and in the paſſage doth eaſily ſtick to the hands of thoſe who have the power to tranſmit it. But Land is an apparent viſible Eſtate, which the Law hath ſo provided for, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be diverted, or conceal'd. And therefore is found ſometimes running in thoſe chanels, which lay off, in a great unlikelyhood, in reſpect of the firſt Fountains; as I could particularly give inſtance in a perſon well known to me, into whoſe hands an Eſtate fell in leſs then twenty years, between whom and it, there were ſix and twenty per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who intervened.</p>
            <p>And here alſo may regard be had, to ſuch Relations whoſe good word and countenance may be an help and furtherance to you in your way: For it is an old ſaying, <hi>A friend at Court, is as good as a pound in a mans purſe:</hi> and there is a kinde of Smock-Simony,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:42531:63"/>which may be more lawful and more gainful then that of the Black-coat; when a man may be Son-in-law, or kinſman to the next good place that falls, or at leaſt may be handed in to ſuch a convenience, as where one may converſe with gain, or by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and counſel may be fairly put on; or by the reflection of the Sun which ſhines on ſuch a friend, may be made more lightſome and perſpicuous to the view of thoſe, which we have a minde ſhould ſee us.</p>
            <p>Having thus fixt upon your choice, the next conſideration is how to obtain her: Wherein 'tis of principal uſe, to diſcover the higheſt affection: for as there is no perſon ſo unlovely, but thinks her ſelf worſhy to be loved; ſo is there a natural inclination in love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o beget love, and (unleſs in ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular exceptions) ſeldom fails of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing, if not ſo much kindneſs, at leaſt ſo much commiſeration, as gives an aptitude to condeſcenſion.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially too, if love be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended with ſuch becoming importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as well admits of no denial; when
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:42531:63"/>Rhetorick is not ſtrained by a bum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſte expreſſion; but ſuch words are found out, as ſeem to be onely dictated by affection, wherein the heart hath the greateſt, and wit no other ſhare, then to give them a lovely pronuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Wherein ſuch conſtancie muſt be obſerv'd, as may give the greateſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of your affection: for women being ſenſible that this is that wherein their ſtrength lyeth, and that they are never likely ſo to domineer, as now, when your hopes are dead or alive as they ſmile or frown; they take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to Tantalize you, and ſhew their own preheminence; and do by you, as thoſe Chirurgions, who though they intend to make a cure at laſt, yet to ſerve their own turns, keep you long in hand, and intermit their lenitive emplaiſters, with thoſe which may cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode and vex you. And in truth, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men never ſo well revenge themſelves on men, as when they ſend them ſneak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away, diſappointed in their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations: and that which is the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief on't, the buſineſs is not acted in a corner, but the world muſt be a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:42531:64"/>witneſs of the defeat; when in the midſt of all your gallantry, you are routed Horſe and Foot, and triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over by ſuch an enemy, as gives no other reaſon why ſhe will not, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe will not.</p>
            <p>And therefore in ſuch caſes, they muſt be dealt with, as Stalkers do with bobbed Partridges, give them time till they may be brought about again: for their own inconſtancie will not let them be long in the ſame minde, but that Weather-cock which ſtands to the cold North to day, you my finde (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) to the warm South to morrow.</p>
            <p>And here obſerve alſo, that there is not a little Rhetorick in gifts; of which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>That they blinde the eyes of the wiſe:</hi> Wherein 'tis diſcretion to make choice of ſuch, as may be not ſo much coſtly as pertinent; ſuch as are likely to gain her acceptance, by fitting her humour, rather then by drayning your purſe; and ſuch too, as may moſt and longeſt be expos'd to view, and be the opportuneſt Orators in your behalf. And for this cauſe your coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treats muſt be of rarer uſe, which are almoſt forgotten as ſoon as the taſte
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:42531:64"/>is off the Palate; and are then onely uſeful, when by their jollity they may allay an auſterer temper, or you are in hopes that by a more publick conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion, there may be a ſtop given to any purpoſes of retracting: Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe doubtleſs privacie affords the beſt woing; and they will then comply moſt, when they may hide their bluſhes in your boſome.</p>
            <p>But if you fail of your expectation, and your ſuit want ſucceſs; let it be your care to come fairly off, by no means indeavouring to abate your diſgrace in the diſappointment, by caſting any blemiſh upon the perſon you have made ſervice to: For as I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways abhorred that love, which becauſe it could not ſpeed, was converted into hate; ſo have I thought their come-off no leſs unworthy, who to qualifie the blemiſh of their being denyed, have made no bones to throw dirt in their faces, where before in their officiouſneſs they would have kiſs'd their breeches. It is therefore doubtleſs more noble to let the world ſee, that you had integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in your intentions, and were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unfortunate then baſe; miſtaken
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:42531:65"/>rather in the thoughts of your own worth, which is common to men, then in the conceptions of her worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and being ſtill deſirous to keep thoſe as friends, whom you cannot obtain as neerer relations: For verily methinks 'tis very unjuſt, not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute thoſe ever with all common courteſies, to whom one ever preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any conjugal pretenſions.</p>
            <p>But if you be ſo ſucceſsful as to obtain, be remembred 'tis now the time to be conſiderately joyful, and to obſerve the golden mean of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated freeneſs: not to laſh out into ſuch extravagance, as may render you ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected to the ſober; nor guilty of any ſuch poorneſs, as may juſtly ſubject you to the cenſure of the wiſer: For as <hi>the day of our eſpouſals,</hi> ſhould be <hi>the day of the gladneſs of our hearts;</hi> ſo is it great folly to let the ſtream then overflow its banks at ſuch a rate, as that the Chanel ſhould be the ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower for it ever after. For though I am no enemy to Nuptial Feaſts, yet I have thought them no leſs then mad, which to fit others with Wedding-Gloves, have brought themſelves in
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:42531:65"/>a few years to want working-day Shooes; running ſo far in debt, to make that one day joyous and paunch-gutted, as hath made all the reſt of their days mournful and pinch-bellyed. Whilſt others therefore wiſh you joy, know the foundation of it muſt be in your ſelves; and that is likely to be moſt, which ſo begins, as that it may hold out, and taketh care that the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the following years may be made (at leaſt) by the pattern of the Wedding Clothes.</p>
            <p>Being now ſafely moared in the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py harbour of a well-diſpoſed wife, let it be your firſt care to promote her Piety; which I do not ſpeak of as 'tis thy duty, but as expedient to advance your content and well-fare: For as doubtleſs 'tis no mean policie to be good; God either giving ſuch his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the things of this life, or recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pencing the want of theſe with the things of a better: So is Religion not the leaſt of thoſe means, whereby all ſocieties are preſerved in their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar intereſt, being call'd <hi>Religio</hi> (as ſome will) <hi>à religando,</hi> binding our mindes
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:42531:66"/>in the conſcience of ſuch duties, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no other conſideration would prevail with us.</p>
            <p>And upon the ſame ſcore, 'tis great prudence to preſerve in the freſheſt greenneſs, that conjugal affection, which if it did not at firſt bring you together, yet doubtleſs ſhould be of prime de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne in this condition; Love being like that Salt and Sugar which doth ſeaſon, and make acceptable thoſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currents, which without it would bite upon the Tongue, and beget diſguſts moſt indiſpenſible. And verily thoſe Husbands are Fools, who think to have the ſubjection of their Wives, not by the exerciſes of affection, but the aſſerting their own authorities: For whatever is compell'd, waits for an opportunity to be deny'd; and they that rule over the unwilling, finde the trouble as great to keep in obedience, as the pleaſure to be obey'd. All com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſory being a violent motion, which upon every ceſſation of the <hi>vis motiva,</hi> returns again to its natural bent; when as that which is from a principle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, moves regularly, and is commonly moſt active in oppoſition. For which
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:42531:66"/>cauſe we read that <hi>Love is as ſtrong as Death,</hi> and <hi>many Waters cannot quench Love;</hi> it being that active affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which makes us willing to do, willing to ſuffer, willing to give, and willing to forgive: for <hi>Love covers a multitude of ſins,</hi> not onely by over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looking them, and allowing the faireſt interpretation to all that will admit it; but by being ready to condone what might be done amiſs, and accepting of any acknowledgement for ſatisfaction: Thus ſodering by a ſpeedy compoſure thoſe caſual breaches, which diſaffecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtill makes wider; ſo that what was at firſt but accidentally offenſive, by after-exaggeration proves to be the cauſe of a final ſeparation. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without doubt there ſhould be the greateſt caution to preſerve this affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on like the Apple of the Eye, which no mote may offend; and to compoſe thoſe ſtrifes with the greateſt ſpeed, which may give an allay to a mutual kindeneſs: for doubtleſs they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable, who upon occaſional diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents affect a ſullenneſs, &amp; think to give a weight to their anger by the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; whereas in very deed, all that
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:42531:67"/>time the Heart frets; and Love, if it do not lye a bleeding, yet grows faint, for want of the exerciſe of kindeneſs; and will not be long ere it fall into a conſumption, if ſuch occurrents be but as frequent, as they are pernicious. And ſurely in this caſe 'tis vain to ſtrain ceremony, and expect who ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply firſt: for we will not ſay who is the ſtouteſt; but of this we are ſure, they that comply firſt, they are the wiſeſt.</p>
            <p>And here obſerve too, that 'tis great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expedient (if ſuch diſputes happen) to avoid all ſuch language as hath any bitterneſs in it: For all ſuch ſinks deep into the minde, and is hardly oblite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated with any after-excuſe, giving cauſe to ſuſpect that it was the iſſue of a feſtered heart, and that a precipitate paſſion did not produce it, but diſcover it: ſo that what might eaſily be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, as to the matter of the offence, proves almoſt remedileſs, as to the words.</p>
            <p>And with this, you may take notice, that nothing is more miſchievous then ſuch an expreſſion, as may profeſs a diſaffection: For aſſure your ſelf, there's
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:42531:67"/>much of wiſdom, even there to make ſemblance of the higheſt love, where 'tis but indifferent; and to behave your ſelf with all ſuch expreſſions of kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as may give no cauſe to ſuſpect that you love not: For if once they are perſwaded of that, they take you for an enemy, and make it their buſineſs to plot againſt you, and lay contrivances to advance their own intereſt with whatſoever hazard of yours. And if once it come to that paſs, you may bid farewel to your peace and content while you live together: For the joynt intereſt between the man and the Wife is the great ſoder of their affairs, that which doth cement their deſignes, and concenter their purpoſes. For as it was ſaid that <hi>they twain ſhall be one fleſh;</hi> ſo is it intended therewith, that their intereſt (twofold before) ſhould become one, that with a joynt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour they may drive on the good of both; which therefore ſhould be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred with as great a caution, as that Rin'd which cauſes the Graft and Stock <hi>coaleſcere,</hi> and thrive toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:42531:68"/>
            <p>For which cauſe, I ever thought it no prudence for man and wife to have two purſes. The Bed and the Purſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two things, wherein a mutual ſharing breeds kindneſs and confidence; and they are ſeldom double, where there is not diviſion. For, as without doubt there is all the reaſon, that ſhe who joyn'd hey Stock to yours, and put in her Portion, ſhould enjoy ſo much of her own, as to pleaſe her ſelf in that to which ſhe hath a particular liking: So is it beſt, that ſhe do that out of the common Purſe; wherein 'tis like ſhe'll uſe greater prudence and moderation, then where ſhe is her own carver without inſpection. And as on the one hand, a private purſe doth incline to a private deſigne, and tends to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote an intereſt that is too particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their own: So on the other hand, where they are kept ſhort, and depriv'd of that freedom to command your purſe in a meaſure that is convenient, they repine at their reſtraint, and either wiſh in their hearts that you were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, or apply themſelves to ſuch ſhifts as are baſe and degenerous; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying their deſires by ſuch unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:42531:68"/>means, as many times prove not onely dedecorous to them, but pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to you: For while you refuſe to ſupply their expences on the ſcore of your kindneſs, they are induc'd to ſeek for thoſe that will; and think it juſt to make repayment in that coyn, which whether you will or no, they muſt have in their own keeping.</p>
            <p>And for this cauſe, it is greatly expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to be as accommodated (as pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence will allow) to the humour of the wife, ſo as may be moſt to her content. For there is none of them which marry with an intent to be ſlaves, but promiſe to themſelves that pleaſure and convenience in your Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which they conceive themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable to enjoy without you; which if they want from you, their own wit induceth them to ſeek elſewhere. Whence it is, that I have known ſome who came to the Bride-houſe with the greateſt affection, promiſing to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as much content in an Husband as their love and good opinion had rais'd their expectations up to; but after, being diſappointed in their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and finding the Tavern and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:42531:69"/>company ſharing ſo deep in what they lookt for, they grew deſperately diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; and thinking it equal to requite their neglect with the like, they ſoon found out thoſe who would attend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them with that courtſhip and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placence which their grumbals would not. And verily who could think the thing unreaſonable? for while friends on both ſides did lament the miſhap, they could not but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that the thing was juſt: For by our nature, <hi>home</hi> is <hi>animal politicum,</hi> and eſpecially the woman, whoſe very creation was for ſociety, and with the deſigne that man might not be alone; and therefore above all things, they hate Anachoriſm, and can with no pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience indure to be mew'd up till mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, while you, it may be, are club<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing it at a Tavern: and you cannot think it a wonder, if at ſuch a time they ſport with your ſervants at home, when you are abroad; which you may judge done not for knavery, but meer divertiſement.</p>
            <p>And further, do but conſider how long that love is like to laſt, where the blundring Husband comes home like
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:42531:69"/>a ſous'd Hogs-head, with a ſteam of ſmoke and drink would almoſt choak a Greenlander, who hath been fed with blubber: Imagine now how acceptable ſuch a Porpiſe muſt needs be to the neatneſs and curioſity of a well-bred woman, who cannot but loath a ſpectacle of that deformity; and cannot but contemn that ridiculous poll, which blatters forth any thing that comes next, to the juſt provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a more ſtayed and temperate judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo that what ſhould deſerve their love and reſpect, becomes the loathed object of their contempt and ſcorn.</p>
            <p>And that which is the miſchief on't too, to ſee the codled fool take upon him in that tune, and exerciſe his Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandly authority, like a Mayor of <hi>Queenborow,</hi> and with as much diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: when the diſcreet woman ſees her head nodding out his commands, with leſs wit then a Gander on a Green; which ſhe does, and laughs at, grieving in her heart that providence hath joyn'd her, where an Horſe and an Aſs muſt draw together: And then you may bid farewel, not onely to
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:42531:70"/>that love which you might have had, but alſo that authority you ſhould have: for never think that that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſubmitteth willingly, to whom her Husband behaves not himſelf like a man of underſtanding.</p>
            <p>And by this you may perceive how much the diſcretion of the man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth to the marring or making of the Wife. For of how many hopeful women doth daily experience give us an account, whom their Husbands fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath miſerably undone, while they have cared rather to be ſerviceable to their own preſent humours, then their future content; or have thought it better to deal in hacking and hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then in a gentle bending thoſe plyant Oſiers, which might eaſily have been wrought, as prudence would have had them?</p>
            <p>And I believe you will finde with an eaſie obſervation, that wives general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are eaſier drawn then driven; and that there are very few, even of the beſt of them, which will fairly bear to be ſowrely told of thoſe things, which yet they are willing to mend. And therefore all ſuch plaiſters muſt be
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:42531:70"/>ſoftly applyed; and a warineſs had, not to finde fault in the hearing of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which may beget a diſtaſt in thoſe things, where no unkindneſs would be taken upon a private rebuke. And in very deed, the reputation of a Wife in this point of her ſufficiencie, ſhould be tendred by us as a choice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, eſpecially among thoſe over whom ſhe exerciſeth any thing of command: For you will ſoon finde a very ſmall matter will give thoſe occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to deſpiſe her authority, who by your conviction ſhall be judg'd worthy of blame. And truely 'tis hard to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate young Wives from the contempt of their Servants; who will much more readily deride their petty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretions, then obey their reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble commands; eſpecially when the new maid is an old play-follow, and is almoſt to learn the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſport and obedience; or is ſome ſtanch Trout that hath been ſo beaten to the world, as hath put her, though not out of the need, yet out of the conceit of being commanded. And therefore to aſſert the Wives authority the more, 'tis beſt that ſhe rule the roaſt altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:42531:71"/>in the houſe; and if you inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, it ſhould be rather by way of advice and aſſiſtance, then ſuperiority. And in very deed they are pittiful ſouls, which can't let the women alone with their Pipkins and Pies, but are peeping to finde fault in the feminine juriſdiction; and eſteem it one of their eminent virtues, that they are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry frugal in Dripping and Kitchin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuff.</p>
            <p>But the truth is, there's a great deal of reaſon that the Wife ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be born with, as the infirmer; there being many occaſions not onely to diſturb their diſcretion, but alſo to perturb their paſſion; the <hi>craſis</hi> of their bodies being more humid, and ſubject to that Planet which is moſt mutable. Beſides the many infirmities which Child-bearing bringeth; the obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, fumes, and opilations which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal their more delicate conſtitutions: up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all which it is meet, we ſhould <hi>give honour to the wife, as the weaker veſſel;</hi> not contending with them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are more robuſt, but bearing with them becauſe we are ſo.</p>
            <p>Yet in all ſuch things wherein you
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:42531:71"/>comply with the deſires of the Wife, 'tis much the beſt to act in it freely: For if they muſt watch to take you in the humour, or work it out of you by their own art, they congratulate their own skill, and acknowledge no kindeneſs; ſo you loſe the thanks, and lay no obligation: whereas the main deſigne ſhould be to ingage af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection by kindneſſes flowing, and not ſtrain'd; and even there, where ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity denyes, the refuſal ſhould be ſo convey'd, as that ſhe may perceive 'twas ſo, becauſe it could not be, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you would not that it ſhould be.</p>
            <p>If providence ſo diſpoſe of you, as that you marry a Wife that brings Children with her by another Husband, as your concerns are more, ſo ought the exerciſes of your prudence too: And the rather, becauſe there lyes on you that general ſuſpition, which all Father-in-laws labour under. And therefore to prevent that, 'tis good to walk by that general rule, To do by them in all things, as if they were your own. And verily this (not onely a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of your duty ſhould induce you
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:42531:72"/>to) being plac'd by providence in the room of a Father; but alſo a dread, leſt ſuch a ſucceſſor ſhould be given you, who may retaliate on yours the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs or injuſtice you have exerciſed to them. And doubtleſs, if ill-gotten goods bring ſuch a canker with them, as ſoon eats out the eſtates they come to; there's none devours with a greater greedineſs, then that of the Orphans and Widows money; God having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that title upon him, that he is the <hi>God of the fatherleſs and widow,</hi> to let the world know, that he hath a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Guardianſhip of the concernments of ſuch, and will himſelf revenge their injuries, though their impotence make them more liable to ſuffer, and leſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to vindicate their ſufferings. And withal, your care ſhould be as ſtudious for their education, that being not the leaſt wherein we ſhew our pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal kindeneſs to thoſe that are ours. And if the Fowls of the Air leave not their youngs ones, till they have ſhew'd them the way to get their own livings; it ſhould be your chief endeavour to do that buſineſs for them, which death prevented their own Father in, that he
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:42531:72"/>could not do. Neither think much that the Mothers kindneſs ſeems moſt to theſe: for there's reaſon that ſhe ſhould compenſate the Fathers loſs with a more abundant tenderneſs, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs that a double-portioned affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which before ran in a duplicated, now but in a ſingle chanel.</p>
            <p>Now ſuppoſing you to be in the way of Houſe-keeping, let me give you ſome of my experiments for your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: and the firſt ſhall be a cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to avoid thoſe Hangers on, that are the flies which attend the fleſh of others Tables, and requite you with their maggots; ſuch as your chare-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and men at a call, who make it their work to rob you under a finer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then that of plain ſtealing; or at beſt, like thoſe beggers who give you an half-farthing wand, that they may receive your twopence. Such as theſe ſhall your ſervants have to ſerve their turn with a wet-finger; and pay them largely, not with their own money, but your meat: which if you connive at, they praiſe you highly, and you are their very good Maſter; and when
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:42531:73"/>they have undone you, ſhall do you this kindeneſs, to ſay 'tis pitty, for <hi>you were no bodies foe but your own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet think not much to be free in the relief of thoſe you know to be poor, and labour with induſtry to get their own livings: For Alms to the idle, is like greaſe to a Cart-wheel, which makes it go round the eaſier, but ſtill upon the ſame axle; whereas ſupply to thoſe who are wanting, yet labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, or impotently neceſſitous, is a debt due to their want; yet of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that while we pay what is their due, God accepts it as a loan, and hath put himſelf under an obligation to make repayment. And truely I have obſerved, that while I have known many undo themſelves with riotous Houſe-keeping, entertaining needleſs gueſts, and idle-bellies; I could never yet meet with any, who could ſay he he was the poorer, nay, not the richer, for ſuch acts of charity, as were done to the needy: But that ſuch diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, like the loaves of our Saviour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the 4000, leave behinde them more baskets of fragments, for the heirs
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:42531:73"/>to give away, then the principal was in quantity, which the Father ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended.</p>
            <p>Yet let me tell you, 'tis no wiſdom to make your ſervants your Almoners, and allow them the liberty of diſpoſing your Charity; for one hand to give, is enough in a purſe. And that Charity is the beſt, which hath the ſpirit of diſcerning; and like that Boy, gives Hony to the Bees, but hath a whip to drive away the drones.</p>
            <p>Be here adviſed too, not to be given to the humour of coſtly entertainments: For I have often ſeen that men of that fancie, have inverted the Calendar, and have found their Faſts after their Feſtivals; who when they have ſpent all, have been as welcome to their gueſts, as a former Wives old Cloathes to a new-marryed Bride. Beſides, the obligation which you lay by your coſt on thoſe which are entertained, is for the moſt part as far below it, as the Church of St. <hi>Faiths</hi> is beneath <hi>Pauls</hi> Steeple. For the moſt at ſuch encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, are more concern'd to cenſure your expence, then acknowledge your kindneſs; and generally jeer at ſome
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:42531:74"/>things you might fail in, rather then fairly accept what you courteouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</p>
            <p>But the entertaiment of great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons is a greater vanity: For ſuch think they oblige you, in doing you the honour to eat up your Cheer; which to them who fare ſumptuouſly every day, is ſcarce lookt upon as extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary; ſo that inſtead of accepting your civility, they reſent it as an affront that it was no richer; and what ſhall be indeed profuſion in you, will be lookt upon but as the Wrens piſſing in the Sea to them.</p>
            <p>But what I have here ſaid of enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, I intend not of ſuch as are accidentally gueſts, perſons that come to viſit in kindeneſs: for unto ſuch as theſe, entertainment is due, and ought to be free, and proportioned to the quality of the perſons concerned, with that heartineſs and plenty, as may abundantly ſpeak for you, that they are welcome: and in very deed, ſuch intercourſes as theſe, are neceſſary to preſerve a mutual friendſhip, and keep alive the remembrance of that kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and relation, which otherwiſe,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:42531:74"/>like unremoved Logs, would grow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that earth, which at firſt begat them.</p>
            <p>But what houſe ſoever you keep when friends are with you, let your ordinary and private fare be never coſtly; but ſuch, as though the beſt in its kinde, yet plain and wholeſome, to fortifie Nature, and nouriſh, not to tickle the Palate: for to pleaſe the dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty tooth, is an expenſive humour, and doubles that charge which Houſe-keeping bringeth; while the ſauce is more then the Meat; and 'tis as dear to cook a Diſh, as to provide it. And verily the vanity of ſome deſerves our wonder, who are of that Heliogaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian ſtomack, to which nothing doth reliſh which is not dear, and fancie fiſh moſt when fartheſt from ſhoar; then onely loving Peaſe, when they are ſearce to be had; and Cherries, when they are ty'd on ſticks.</p>
            <p>In buying proviſions, be your own Caterer; wherein at leaſt you may have this convenience, that you may pleaſe your ſelt. Beſide, however faithful your ſervant may be, ſo that he lets down no g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ats without a ſtrain; you
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:42531:75"/>cannot expect that he ſhould part with your coyn, with that care and difficulty as you would your ſelf, whoſe daily feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how much proviſion doth pinch, makes wary, and hard to be drawn to expence.</p>
            <p>But be chiefly advis'd not to run on the ſcore; for you may be aſſured, that with greater advantage you may take up money at uſe to pay ready down: For there's none of them all, but reckon how they forbear, and will be ſure to be allow'd, not onely becauſe they muſt ſtay for their money, but truſt; there being nothing ſo certain in this world, as that which is preſent. You will alſo finde that a true Proverb, <hi>That the beſt is beſt cheap:</hi> For beſides that in fleſh, there's much the leſs quantity of bones for the weight, where they are covered almoſt twice of the thickneſs; in all other things you'll finde much the leſs waſte, becauſe that which is good goes down without ſcraps, while parings and refuſe go a great way in what is not. Servants making no ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to caſt that to the Dogs, which they are ſoon apt to think is not good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:42531:75"/>
            <p>Be you alſo aſſur'd, that the beſt of Servants muſt be over-lookt: for it is rare to finde thoſe, who will not make waſte: and as it is fit they ſhould have to the full, their meat being a great part of the wages of their work; ſo are there few, but do labour under ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of bread; and none that conſider of what they would be glad, when they come to keep a poor houſe of their own.</p>
            <p>In your buying Proviſions, you'll finde it the beſt to go to their Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains: for the farther from thence, ſo much the dearer. There being no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond-hand but ſo licks his own fingers, as that while he hath his gains, the Commodity is inhanc'd; and that which is his livelihood, muſt be what you give more then he paid.</p>
            <p>'Tis alſo beſt to buy by the great: All Chapmen complying much ſooner for much then for a little; their gains by ſo much being the more conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and their put-off the greater. But then muſt your expenditor be wary, and ſo give out the ſtore which you have provided, as remembring the place to ſpare, is never at the bottom.
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:42531:76"/>Beſide the much more eaſineſs to lurch the greater quantities, where a little ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken is not diſcerned: for which cauſe, it is not ſafe to truſt a Servant at an whole heap; there being very few of that integrity, as then to keep their hands from picking, when none can witneſs they did prevaricate; or if they be ſuch, it is not ſafe to tempt with op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity.</p>
            <p>If God ſhall give you Children, it is the duty which each Mother to her off-ſpring owes, to be its Nurſe, as well as Bearer; and therefore not to be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, but then onely when neceſſity makes the excuſe: but if you put them abroad, chuſe out a Nurſe by theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections; whereof I have had ſo good experience, that in the placing out of fourteen of you, I never yet had cauſe to remove one, till it was time that you ſhould be brought home.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let her be a lively woman; thoſe ſtiring ſpirits not onely having fewer dregs to make their milk unwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, but their cheerfulneſs exhila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates the Babe, and gives it a more pleaſurable life and motion too; while
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:42531:76"/>ſuch whoſe mettle can't abide to ſit, muſt dance the childe about, or give it ſome ſuch agitation and divertiſement; when lumpiſh women let it hang in arms, till it be almoſt cripled for want of change.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Then let her be healthy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexioned, of ſuch freſh ruddineſs, as gives account ſhe's not infirm: But chiefly care that ſhe have no heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry miſchief, ſuch as may be ſuckt in by yours unto its detriment, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let her be ſuch a woman too as is much given to be cleanly; ſo great conducement unto health, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon neatneſs in us all: But eſpecially in ſuch little ones, whom Nature hath not moulded to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but that 'tis purging out a more abundant excrement: For which cauſe, we may daily ſee the very Brutes officious in this kinde of care.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Then be ſhe ſuch an one as lives not by the penny, but hath a Cow or two at leaſt, or ſuch ſupplies as may prevent the pinching of the belly through want: For where the purſe
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:42531:77"/>muſt bleed for every pint of Milk the Childe muſt eat, 'twill be not much improbable it many times may go without. Whence 'tis obſerv'd, that meant is much leſs free in all ſuch houſes (howſoever rich) where all comes in by daily purchaſe, then at the Farmers, from whoſe Barns and Stores there come ſupplies, for which no preſent money was expended.</p>
            <p>Be careful too, the Husband be not given unto drink: for at ſome time or other, he'll come home in ſuch a tune, as may indanger much the little weakling. And if in ſuch diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances they many times do miſchief to themſelves, 'tis not but to be feared a greater miſchief may accrue to ſuch a little one as cannot help its ſelf.</p>
            <p>And it is beſt there be agreement 'twixt the man and wife: for none can tell what hair-brain'd tricks there may be done, when they are in a rage; or how the Childe may ſuffer then, when they can ſcarcely be diſtinguiſhed from thoſe are mad: For ſuch conteſts which happen between men and wives, are moſtly managed in ſo much heat,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:42531:77"/>as frequently produce ſuch actions as we then repent of, when we cannot help.</p>
            <p>If thus you are provided, be not then too haſty in the fetching of it home: at two years end is ſoon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; and that's confirm'd by my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in not a few, all kept abroad till they could run about the houſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</p>
            <p>But when they are brought home, be not a means to ſpoil your hopes with too much fondneſs. The leſs the Childe is loll'd in Arms, the better. And by ſo much the food of it be good &amp; plainer, by ſo much healthier you ſhall have it: For all ſweet things do cloy the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack; and dyet multiplyed in varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, doth poſe concoction to digeſt it, which better deals with ſimple food; from whence much eaſier, and more ſurely, it doth contract a firmer nourith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And though Phyſicians gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally decry the uſe of Milk, as too too Phleginatick, and not convenient; yet doth mine own experience as much aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert it; there being ten of you, who I believe may vye with ſuch a number of
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:42531:78"/>any one mans in the world beſide, for health, ſtrength and ſtraitneſs, who have been all true Trojans at a Milk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowl.</p>
            <p>And ſurely it is beſt, not to ſtint Children in their food; ſo that ſuppers be light, and not too neer to bedward: For thoſe that are, are generally made more greedy by denyal; and if they light on opportunity, will gorge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a ſurfeit; when they that u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually feed while they will, know when they have enough; and make not much then to give out, when as their fare is of the daintieſtieſt.</p>
            <p>'Tis alſo beſt to break your Children of their wills, e'en with the ſooneſt; and bring them to that paſs, to know your will, not theirs, muſt be their Law: For 'tis a plague that's moſt intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, to pleaſe them in their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours; and as pernicious to themſelves, there being ſometimes a neceſſity their mindes ſhould not be followed, which then they fret and ſume at to their hurt; when as, when once they're taught but to ſubmit, and kept to that, they forthwith leave off to diſpute, and readily comply with that, which not
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:42531:78"/>their fancie, but your judgement ſhall think fit; and without blubbering, and ſtir, and cryes, give up themſelves to a ſilent obedience: which is moſt eaſily effected by ſuch a conſtant tenor of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, as is not in and out, but they made certain what to truſt to.</p>
            <p>Be alſo here advis'd, not to torment your Children with the curioſity of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, when they (to keep their cloaths neat) muſt be reſtrained from exerciſe, as neceſſary for their health, as is their meat. Nature having ſo diſpos'd the inclination of young things, that they are game ſome all in ſuch a meaſure, that the more ſlothful creatures are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lively in then youths; and the young Calves and Lambs do skip and play, while their more ſober dams look gravely on: And 'tis becauſe there are more moſt and cruder h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nours or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to afford a freer nouriſhment for ſupply of growth, that ſtand in need of a diſcuſſion, and digeſtion more abundant. And veray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>fe's none of us, though much in lined to deny our ſelves to ſerve our pride, but think it a reſtraint, vexatious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:42531:79"/>to be confin'd to <hi>touch not, raſte not, handle not.</hi> And 'tis well worth the laughter, when the mimick Dame is trickt as neat as hands can make her, to ſee with what a caution ſhe's aware, leſt ought ſhould touch her that defiles; and is in need of a glaſs cover, where bravery may well be ſeen, and yet ſecur'd. Then what vexation is it for a childe that's full of life, and fond of play, to be kept in without a motion, leſt it ſhould foul its apron, or put a knot or curl out of its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſcituation!</p>
            <p>When they're grown big enough to ſend to School, 'tis beſt to place them out at board: for Children when put out to board, are taught be times to make their party good with others; and learn ſome meaſure in that art, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee their own concerns, which they have ſo much need of in the world. For in a kinde of little Commonwealth they learn thoſe ſubtilties in ſmaller Volumes, which afterward doth help their practice in their weightier affairs; when thoſe more elderly trapan the younger, till they abus'd, grow wiſer, and learn more wit by their experience,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:42531:79"/>which they ſoon exerciſe upon the reſt. And ſurely I have ſeen ſo much of craft among theſe young ones, to bring to paſs their projects, and cunning wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs to ſhun and diſappoint an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite contrivement; that I have thought it could not be, that any Cat ſhould mouſe ſo well, as that thus pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd in all taking arts, when but a kitling.</p>
            <p>Beſides the great advantage of their mutual deriſion, when 'tis a ſhame to do thoſe things which are unhandſome, which they'll not fail to vex the faulty with; by which means I have known ſome ſoon reclaim'd, when ſober coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, yea too, and correction was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out effect.</p>
            <p>Nor is the help which they afford each other in their learning leſs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable; when thoſe leſs knowing may conſult the wiſer, and have a ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more accommodate unto their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, then by inſtruction that is ſupereminent.</p>
            <p>They are too, under ſuch a conſtant Diſcipline, ſo over-lookt, and ſixt to mulde the main deſigne, and ſet beſide occaſions of diverſion; that without
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:42531:80"/>doubt, if God do give wherewith to bear the charge, there's no expedient like this for their Education; provided that you uſe the greateſt caution, both for their manners, and their learning: For great are the impreſſions that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pre gives in that to waxy age, which generally is prone to cloſe with that which in its conſequences is perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</p>
            <p>For which cauſe I've obſerved many tincted with ſuch looſer habits, as have undone their Fathers hopes, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted them to ſuch a dirſolution, was irrecoverable. Beſides too, the loſs of time, when plac'd with thoſe whoſe faculties afford not, or negligence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours not that he ſhould be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd, is of that ſort which hardly can admit of a redemption; when ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of inſtruction are knockt out by following caſts, which are more fit to kiſs the miſtreſs of their preſent age.</p>
            <p>'Tis therefore beſt to place them where they may be in a conſtant courſe of pions government, with ſuch who are not factiouſly Religious, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the practice of it then the prat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:42531:80"/>and for the power of it then the ſhew: For you muſt know, an high concernment is depending here, and the eternal intereſt of a ſoul. Good E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation having ſuch an influence on the future life, that God takes <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> ſeed as members of his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, becauſe he knew their nurture would be pions, <hi>that he would teach his children, and his houſhold after him.</hi> And truely this might be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive, not onely with the ſober-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but with thoſe too, lets piouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected: For there are few ſent out from Schools, where a prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us hath been predominant, which have not proved very diſſolute; as might be inſtane'd in, in many hundreds, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient.</p>
            <p>Therefore let the Maſter be of that unblameableneſs, as may give greateſt confidence no ill example may be given: For if the beſt of us are more inclin'd to follow thoſe that lead us by pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, then by precept; ſurely thoſe ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der years, (leſs capable to judge the verity of what is ſaid, and have their will conducted by their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) may well be tincted with that
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:42531:81"/>dye they ſee their leaders coloured with.</p>
            <p>Let him be alſo not a Linguiſt onely, a perſon skill'd in, and able to teach the Tongues; but alſo one that hath a lively fan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie, and expreſſive: for little is it for to ſpeak, if not to ſpeak to purpoſe, or with ſuch taking efficacie as may lead captive the affections: and truely matter moſt important, if not laid down with ſuch array of words and elegancie as becomes it, doth ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom take even wiſer judgements, unleſs in the immediate exerciſe of a ſevere diſcretion, and odds as much, as beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cloath'd in rags, and ſet out in its rich attire. And ſuch a witty Genius thus inſtill'd into thoſe greener heads when firſt inform'd, is like a daſh of Musk and Amber, which gathers ſtrength by atter-uſe, and gives an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent perfume unto thoſe things, which otherwiſe would prove but mean.</p>
            <p>And let him have an art to mould the Tongue unto a graceful Elocution, and ſuch a way of Speech as runs like Oyl, and ſmoothly ſtroaks the Ear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an itch would ſtill be farther ſcratcht;
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:42531:81"/>For what advantage is't, when tender Tongues are timely ſet in tune! which makes the ſelf-ſame matter differ from its ſelf, as much as <hi>Bowbel</hi> chimes do from the clanging of a Kettle.</p>
            <p>Let him be too of a Gentile and generous demean, a perſon ſet beyond the ſtate of a meer Scholar, whom Learning hath no farther favour'd then the head; but one that fetcheth thence a fair accompliſhment for all concerns; when like to woaded Cloth, he takes all other dyes with greater luſtre and more eaſe: One that may ſet impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions on their youth of all gentiler qualities, and give them ſuch a taſt of noble-mindedneſs, as may beget in them a value of their reputations; and takes them off from what's unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, with giving them a ſenſe that it's below them. Which way to deal with youth, is as far beyond the courſe of that ſeverity which onely practiſeth with them as with ſlaves, fit for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nurture then of blows, as is a principle of inward life, above that motion which is onely violent: For when as the one ceaſeth with the force, and is no longer then the fear
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:42531:82"/>indures; the other (when once ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited) will bear them company unto their Graves; and when they're men, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain their thoughts from what is vile, and be a ſpur to ſuch deſignes as may prove noble and heroick. And who can think it is a mean to breed up liberal Children and ingenuous, to cow their ſpirits, and depreſs them to ſuch a dirty ſervileneſs, as knows no ſpur, but that of ſmart, and acts all duty ſtill in the <hi>Bridewel</hi> of ſevere correction? And Government, which ſhould have following obedience drawn after it by ſence of benefit and kindeneſs, is like to tyranny with hang and draw, driving before it thoſe, who onely do, becauſe they muſt; being beaten out of love with what they ſhould delight in, by being beaten. When the proud <hi>Poedagogue</hi> ſtruts in his ſtate, his Lads like quaking puddings all about him; and thinks that Boy will prove a Rebel, which looks not with as much abject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, as <hi>Venus</hi> when trapan'd by <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can.</hi> And don't you think that Youths when thus brought to their poſtures, to ſtand like Vagabonds faſt at a Whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping-poſt; or at the beſt, like ſneaking
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:42531:82"/>Taylors, are in a mighty forwardneſs to act their parts on the Worlds Stage, and be brought forth to ſuch prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence, as by their birth and wealth they may have hopes of!</p>
            <p>And verily it is of great importance, that he who hath the government of youth, ſhould be a perſon of a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcretion; as being (not onely to bend their irregularities by the rectitude and ſtraitneſs of unerring principles, &amp; give fixation to the fluctuating of their wilde and looſer thoughts by ſuch a Diſcipline as keeps them ſtill intent to all the documents and exerciſes of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue) but alſo to over-ſee the manners of ſo many, and with all vigilancie to prevent the pullulating of thoſe roots of bitterneſs their hearts are full of: To deal in bending every ſlip, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly as it can bear it: To have diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their different affections, and move them all, by ſuch expedients as are accommodated moſt unto their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral inclinations: To moderate in all their differences, and give ſuch judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as may eaſily evince his equani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity unto them all. How great his prudence ſhould be, and his moderation,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:42531:83"/>that ſhall be judge without Law, of what ſhall be done amiſs, making what he pleaſe an offence, and puniſhing that offence as he pleaſe. What judgement to diſcern the difference of tempers, and chuſe out that diverſity of application, which is to be diſpens'd as is moſt ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to each particular Genius; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al the condeſcention too, to the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of youth, and the allowance muſt be made unto thoſe brains which are but griſtles, and difficultly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend what conceiv'd is as plain as is a Pike-ſtaff, there being nothing-hard to thoſe that do already know it.</p>
            <p>But verily you'll find no choicer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, then that his ſpirit be elate and generous, and ſuch as naturally ſcorns to ſtoop to thoſe things that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſome, though no eye be conſcious: For great are opportunities which do occur to thoſe that have the Tutorage of Youth, to over-bear them for their own advantage, and to compenſate that wherein they looſe, by freedom from thoſe puniſhments, which like the Papal Pargatory they carry in their keeping. Beſide the manifold tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to pinch them in their dyet, which
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:42531:83"/>no expedient can prevent in the dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous and ſordid-ſpirited: and no man wiſely can commit the ſuſtenance of his, which ſhould be free, and of the largeſt, to ſupply the growth of youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger years, unto ſuch baſe and avari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious tempers, as think there's nothing vile which doth bring gain.</p>
            <p>When placed thus abroad, be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that you don't divert their ſtudies, nor interrupt their ſtrict attendance by avocations home, at any time which is not general: for all ſuch callings off, don't onely intermit the buſineſs they're imploy'd in, and looſe that time which might be profitably ſpent; but they go retrograde, and looſe thoſe things which they had got: Their Memories, like leakie Casks, ſoon letting out thoſe rudiments which were with greateſt difficulty there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtil'd. And which is worſe, they're thereby taken off and made leſs apt for thoſe impreſſions which Learning gives, while love of idleneſs and play is more habituate, and they diſturb'd in application of their thoughts, by the remembrance of that pleaſure which they had at home.</p>
            <pb n="166" facs="tcp:42531:84"/>
            <p>But though you keep them thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, yet let them ſtill be furniſhed with ſuch ſupplies of money as you may conceive are ſuitable to ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence as Children uſe: for thereby they'll be well inſtructed in that wari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and caution, which is required in all bargain-making, and in that petty trading that's among themſelves, and loſs, it may be of to them ſome preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pence, they learn the art to deal in greater matters, and ſhun decoys which might draw in to things of diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
            <p>But when at home, or when abroad, be careful ever to exact an abſolute o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, to have your will obſerved as a law; for by that means you'll much facilitate your government of them, and make by cuſtom much more tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable all their deſignes to you; which may be done with as much eaſe as love, provided that the courſe be conſtant, whence Youth like Naggs which are well pac'd, will take pleaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in't.</p>
            <p>When now they're fit to put into the World, be careful that, and now, you
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:42531:84"/>do diſpoſe them; for there's no loſs ſo great, as not to be put in a Way; nor can there be a greater miſchiet done us, then not to be bred up to ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient imployment; nay though pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for with a moſt large ſubſiſtence: For doubtleſs there's not one whom God deſignes to be an idle drone, when we read <hi>Adam,</hi> though in Paradiſe, was ſet to fill the Ground; nor any that was made onely for ſport and recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And verily, a viler race we hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know, then thoſe among us, whoſe paſtime is their onely buſineſs, and their conſults how they may ſpend their time and their eſtates, in Riot, Cards and Dice; and rack their labouring Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, to ſupply their prodigal exceſſes: Contemning thoſe as pittiful Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks, who by ſome uſeful art conduce to Commonwealth, while they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are without any Myſterie, and onely know ſuch arts as make them vile. Therefore if God ſhall ſo far bleſs you, as that you have an ample patrimony to bequeath to yours; yet bring them up in ſome ſuch way, wherein they may be uſeful unto com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good, and able to promote their
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:42531:85"/>own concerns: For there's no reaſon that's more evident (except Gods curſe upon ill-gotten goods) why ſuch E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates which Fathers in the City get, are quickly run out by their Heirs, then that they're bred up, not to get, but ſpend. Beſide the common penury of thoſe (even in their large re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues) who have no means to add to, but do ſpend their yearly income, whereby their wants of money greater are, then thoſe who by ſome gainful Trade provide for their own main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. Hence do we daily ſee thoſe Gentlemen out-vy'd, who onely live upon their means, though of ſome hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds by the year, by ſuch mean Trades, which by a wary and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious management, afford a fairer and more free ſubſiſtence, and have a ready caſh ſupply'd by daily gettings; when thoſe with empty pockets long for the rent-day, with an anxious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectance. And which is worſe, their Children, which have been bred up to bear a ſhare in ſport and prodigal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, are at the end turn'd off with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any portions ſuitable to the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they have been bred in; whereby
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:42531:85"/>they become pittiful Paraſites, to lick their fingers at elder Brothers Tables; or if they have more ſpirit, ſeek their Fortunes by ſuch expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, as do conclude them in untimely ends.</p>
            <p>But be advis'd of two things, in the diſpoſing of your Children into the World.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Weaken not your Eſtate ſo far for their proviſion, as that it grow faint, and not able to hold out for your own handſome ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence: For though the ſtock ſhould be free for the ſupply of the Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; yet ſo, as that there may be to keep its ſelf lively. I my ſelf knew a perſon of good worth, the gray Hairs of whoſe Eſtate lookt thin for lack of moiſture, which was too freely expended upon his nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous off-ſpring; and I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten griev'd at the ſight of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments, to ſee his Chanel brought ſo low, as unable to bear a weighty Veſſel, meerly to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford a larger current for his deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <pb n="170" facs="tcp:42531:86"/>
            <p n="2">2. So order your matters, that your Children may ever know, that <hi>the branches bear not the root, but the root them;</hi> and ſo reſerve your Eſtate in your own hands, as to command their obedience by their future expectances. For as 'tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trograde, that the River ſhould go back to feed the Fountain, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren treaſure up for their Parents; ſo is it rare to finde out that affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ſhall aſcend to ſuch a proportion as it deſcended. And the vaſt experience which the World af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords of perſons whoſe indulgence hath undone them, and laid them proſtrate unto their contempts, whom (had they ſtill reſerved what to beſtow) they might have found as ſervient to their nods; may well induce the warieſt caution here, and make you wiſe ſtill to retain the power, as to command the ſpitting in your Parlour while you live.</p>
            <p>And now you are ſuppos'd to be in the laſt paſſage of your life, like
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:42531:86"/>ripened Corn in ſuch a tendencie, as gives back to the Earth that bare it. And here be not concern'd in ſuch contrivancie, as may deſigne a pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous Funeral; for coſt expenſively laid out on that, will very little turn unto account; and don't agree with ſuch reflects as ſhould be made by us upon our Graves. It more concerns us to take care to make us friends of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Mammon, and be ſuch Stewards of thoſe things with which the heavenly providence hath intruſted us, as beſt agrees with thoſe deſignes, for which he hath profeſt that he doth give them to us. And though there be no merit in Alms-deeds, as Popiſh Doctrine would perſwade us; yet <hi>to do good, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, are ſuch ſacrifices where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God is well pleaſed.</hi> And there is much in that Speech of the Angel to <hi>Cornelius, Thy prayers and alms-deeds are come up in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance before God;</hi> being there rendred as the reaſon why <hi>Peter</hi> with the Goſpel is ſent unto him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the many promiſes made of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payment
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:42531:87"/>of what ſhall be ſo laid out; ſo that it is not to be doubted, but the beſt uſe that we can make of our goods, is, that they be imployed in the relief of the neceſſitous; and that the beſt way to treaſure up, is ſo to ſpend. If therefore God ſhall bleſs your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with increaſe, remember that there is always this intereſt due to him; and while you take care to provide for your own Family, let not Gods Houſhold (the poor) be unprovided for: which will be an expedient ſo to take your leave of this the preſent world, as that your <hi>exit</hi> may be with a <hi>plaudite.</hi> And ten times better 'twill be for you to have the poor to follow your dead corpſe, with their acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgements of your Charity and Alms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds, then to have the Town-talk of you, that you left thouſands behinde you in your Coffers. And verily, that is an unthrifty providence, that with a many bags deſignes to make a purchaſe of the Town-talk, which for the moſt part proves to be ſiniſtrous, when much more happily we may be carryed hence, perfum'd with that acceptable
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:42531:87"/>remembrance which our perſpicuous vertues leave behind us; and if we may call this ambition, there's certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no better can befal us.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42531:88"/>
            <pb n="175" facs="tcp:42531:88"/>
            <head>A Diſcourſe on the Worth of a Good Name.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Eccleſ. <hi>Cap. 7. Verſ. 1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>A good man is better then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious oyntment.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WE read, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.7. of a woman pouring an ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſter-box of oyntment on the head of Jeſus; and <hi>John</hi> 12.3. we are told the perſon and the quantity; but the action there, is not applyed to the head, but to the feet of Jeſus: Not that this was not the ſame time when the oyntment was poured on his head, or that <hi>John</hi> miſtook the head for the feet; but that the Spirit might relate both the anoynting of his feet, and therewith <hi>Mary</hi>'s wiping his feet with her hair; and the end of both, which is there declared, that it might be <hi>for his burial;</hi> and the reaſon of that, from the practice of the Jews, who were wont to anoynt the bodies
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:42531:89"/>of the dead; and that, not onely that by the odour and fragrancie they might prevent any leſs acceptable ſmell, which the body might offend with, but (I ſuppoſe) more chiefly to preſerve the body from putrefaction: For which cauſe we read, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.56. of <hi>ſpices and oyntments,</hi> prepared for the body of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. And this their cuſtom, 'tis like, was continued from the time of <hi>Jacob,</hi> whom <hi>Joſeph</hi> commanded his Phyſitians to embalme, done with ſo much curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, that forty days were ſpent about it; and that, but the uſual rate of thoſe who were embalmed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.3. And this <hi>ad perpetuandam memoriam mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuorum,</hi> which all Nations have had a deſire to.</p>
            <p>Some by ſtately Structures and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres of higheſt value, as <hi>Artemiſia</hi> by her Husband <hi>Mauſolus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some by material repreſentations; as the Romans by their <hi>imagines Majorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some by Cities built, or Caſtles, and called after their own names; as <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Great by that in <hi>Egypt;</hi> and of later times, the Duke <hi>d' Alva</hi> by the Citadel at <hi>Antwerp;</hi> four Towers of which bare the Characters of his Name and Title.</p>
            <pb n="177" facs="tcp:42531:89"/>
            <p>And ſome by preſerving the body in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire by curious oyntments and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balmings; at which the Egyptians were ſuch excellent Artiſts, that I have read of one body, kept in its due ſhape for two thouſand years: and to this preſervation of the memory doth the Text allude, preferring <hi>a good name</hi> to that purpoſe, before <hi>precious oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For putting the queſtion in the laſt verſe of the former Chapter, <hi>Who can tell what ſhall be after him under the Sun?</hi> What remembrance there ſhall be of a man after he is gone hence; he adds, <hi>A good name is better then preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous oyntment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that you may ſee here, as it were, the Wiſeman ſtepping forth with a pair of ballances in his hand, and therein weighing <hi>a good name</hi> againſt <hi>precious oyntment;</hi> upon which truti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation you have the cenſure given on the right-hand, that a good name is the better.</p>
            <p>In the words we may obſerve,
<list>
                  <item>1. What is here preferr'd <hi>A good name.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. To what it is preferr'd as the better, o <hi>precious oyntment.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="178" facs="tcp:42531:90"/>
            <p>In the handling whereof, we will firſt ſhew what a good name is, and then why the beſt embalming.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt: a Good name is a laudable conception of a perſon which hath ſeiſed the mindes of others, ariſing from ſomething of worth, which they apprehend by him.</p>
            <p>This conception ariſeth from ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing whereby we perceive a perſon to have gone beyond the common rate of men, or at leaſt common corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption.</p>
            <p>Whence divers perſons have obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good names, as they have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By ſome profitable invention, whereby they have been uſeful in their Generation to the good of others; in which reſpect we finde the Scriptures recording, <hi>Jabal the father of them that dwell in tents,</hi> and <hi>Tubal-Cain the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructor of every artificer, Gen.</hi> 4.20, 22. Thus alſo in heathen Story we finde the memories celebrated of <hi>Eurialus,</hi> the firſt inventer of Houſes, and <hi>Triptolimus</hi> of the Plow. And ſo that <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the inventer of Printing; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate by name, and by ſucceſs, ſhall
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:42531:90"/>not want an honourable remembrance while the Preſs knows how to imprint Characters in his Memorial. And thus thoſe Philoſophers, the Inventers of curious and ingenious diſcoveries, perpetuated their Memories to Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Monument is ſtill laſting in his Writings when the coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sepulchre of <hi>Mauſolus</hi> is no where to be found.</p>
            <p>And this is ſuch an embalming, that the Heathen deified thoſe who were the Inventers of profitable Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; as <hi>Liber</hi> the finder out of Wine, and <hi>Ceres</hi> of Corn, enrolled in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of their gods.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By being publick-ſpirited, and willing for the general good to deny their ſelf-intereſt. Thus <hi>Cym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian is memoris'd not one'y for his Piety to his Father, and his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial acts, but eſpecially for his Charity, in that he laid his great Poſſeſſions com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon for the poor Athenians in a great ſcarcity of Victuals. Thus we have the <hi>Decii, Horatii,</hi> and <hi>Fabii,</hi> regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring their names among the Romans, in that they accounted it <hi>Dulce pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patria mori.</hi> And the Scriptures re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:42531:91"/>
               <hi>Jehojada,</hi> buryed among the Kings, becauſe he had <hi>done good to Iſrael,</hi> 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 24.16.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By being uſeful to promote and advance the concernments of their own Families, by providence and induſtry; whence that Houſwife in the Proverbs, who <hi>conſidereth a field and buyeth it,</hi> &amp;c. is diſmiſt with this Elogium, <hi>Give her of the fruit of her hands, and let her own works praiſe her in the gates,</hi> Prov. 31.31. When thoſe unprofitable drones, who ſpend their time to trick up themſelves, that they may ſee and be ſeen, periſh in their own rottenneſs. And when ſuch as refuſe to give to the poors bellies, that they may make gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant their own backs, ſhall like a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle expire in their own ſtinks: Then the dead <hi>Dorcaſſes</hi> ſhall have <hi>the coats and garments ſhew'd, which they made while they lived to cloath the naked with;</hi> and ſhall be followed out of the world with this diſcourſe, that they were <hi>full of good works, and alms-deeds which they did,</hi> Act. 9.36, 39.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By being publick-bleſſings to the places where they live, to the Families they have been of, like <hi>chariots and
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:42531:91"/>horſes,</hi> for publick defence and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.14. like <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and <hi>David;</hi> ſuch as leave behinde them, not onely imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table acts, like <hi>the faith of the Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother Lois, and the Mother Eunice;</hi> but in the remembrance alſo of whom, God ſhould pleaſe to do good to their Poſterities, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 8.19. ſuch who are for Walls and Bulwarks; for whoſe ſakes God will ſpare a ſinning people.</p>
            <p n="5">5. By being exemplary in acts of Moral vertue. Thus we have <hi>Ariſtides</hi> regiſtred for his Juſtice, <hi>Regulus</hi> for his fidelity, <hi>Scipio</hi> for his continencie, <hi>Curtius</hi> for his moderation, who was Dictator <hi>ab aratro;</hi> and <hi>Tubero</hi> for his contented poverty, who did <hi>caenare fictilibus in ipſo Capitolio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. By Faith and Patience, and the exerciſes of Grace; by which ſome have purchaſed <hi>better names then of ſons and daughters,</hi> Iſai. 56.5. Whence the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Ye have heard of the patience of Job.</hi> Ye have heard of the faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie of <hi>the three children:</hi> and you may ſee a Catalogue of Worthies,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:42531:92"/>whom it hath pleaſed God himſelf to regiſter, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. of whom 'tis ſaid, <hi>All theſe obtained a good report;</hi> ſuch whoſe names are written, not in earth onely, but alſo in heaven.</p>
            <p>Now why ſuch a <hi>good name</hi> is <hi>better then precious oyntment</hi> preſerving the memory more then the beſt embalming, will appear, it we conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is the moſt certain expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to continue our Memorial: a man may be deprived of other means, which he may deſigne to himſelf, by the iniquity or Executors; but this a man is ſure himſelf to put out of doubt. <hi>Miltiades</hi> the Athenian, though forbidden burial, yet hath raiſed up to himſelf a never-dying Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument by his vertues. And <hi>Supio,</hi> though inter'd in his own houſe, hath left his memory better preſerv'd then if he had been preſſed with a Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramid.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is the moſt durable. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> rob'd and ſpoil'd the Sepulchre of <hi>David,</hi> but could not ſpoil his memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: that God himſelf remembers many years after that he was fallen aſleep, as an argument why he ſhould
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:42531:92"/>ſhew mercie to his Poſterity. This is the way to place a mans Memorial be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the reach of men. It ſometimes ſo falls out, that thoſe who by their Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral-pomp have been plac'd <hi>inter ſuperos,</hi> among the Gods above; at the next turn have been diſpatch'd <hi>ad inferos,</hi> rendred vile and accurſed by all imaginable indignities: Like <hi>Claudius Caeſar</hi> whom <hi>Seneca</hi> reigns to be thruſt out of Heaven, and ſent down to Hell. But a good name admits of none of theſe miſadventures, often ſhining brighter by obſcuration: as <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ritus</hi> ſaith of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſius</hi> and <hi>Brutus,</hi> whoſe Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figies were not ſhew'd it the Funeral of <hi>Junia; Praefulgebant Caſſius, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eo ipſo, quod effigies eorum non viſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That it is the moſt perpetual expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient: Not onely moſt durable againſt the force of men, but alſo moſt perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent againſt the tyranny of time. This is it which that <hi>Edax rerum</hi> can make no prey of. But when the moſt laſting Marbles fret, and prove un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful unto their inſcriptions; when a deluge of forgetfulneſs drowns the moſt pompous Funerals; then <hi>a good
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:42531:93"/>name</hi> ſhall buoy up the memory, and preſerve it from the common inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That this is an expedient of our own making. Embalmings, coſtly Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres, are done for us, not done by us: But <hi>a good name</hi> is that whereby we embalme our ſelves. 'Twas a true Maxime of the Stoicks, <hi>Quae extra ſunt, noſtra non ſunt,</hi> like that of the Poet, <hi>Et genus, &amp; proavos, &amp; quae non fecimus ipſi, vix ea noſtra voco.</hi> But in this, like the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> we gather together for our ſelves ſpices, and celebrate our own Funerals.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That God himſelf is willing in this reſpect to be the Phyſitian, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balm the deceaſed with this ſort of embalming. You may therefore ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, how that through the whole Book of the <hi>Kings,</hi> the Lord is pleaſed to break the boxes of his ſweet Odors over the Sepulchres of the good Kings; ſo that as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. <hi>When the earthly houſe of this taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle ſhall be diſſolved, we have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands:</hi> So may we ſay here, that when the ſtately Sepulchres of the interred,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:42531:93"/>ſhall crumble into duſt, then ſhall the good men have their Epitaphs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>not made with hands,</hi> but ſuch a Sepulchre, <hi>whoſe maker and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. That this puts a vaſt difference between thoſe that are embalmed with it, and ſuch who are not. We in our thoughts put no great odds between two wicked men, though the one lye under a ſtately Monument, the other on a dung-hill, but we fear that they may be both gone to their own place: But we have a far different eſtimate of a good man, though caſt out into the Common-ſhore, then we have of any wicked perſon, however ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly interred: For which cauſe we finde ſo vaſt a difference made between the <hi>exit</hi> of <hi>Jehoram,</hi> and that of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 21.20. and 35.29.</p>
            <p>The Text thus explained, may be applyed,</p>
            <p>Firſt, for our inſtruction in theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hereby we may ſee the way, how we may emerge out of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Grave, how we may render our aſhes diſcernable, among thoſe which
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:42531:94"/>are caſt out into the common Urn: How to diſappoint Death, that great Leveller, that with his Sythe cuts all down, and lays all in the Swarths of the wide field of this world: How, though a <hi>Diogenes,</hi> you may beard an <hi>Alexander;</hi> when thoſe who cauſed ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in the land of the living, <hi>lye all down in the pit among the uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed</hi> in the grave, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 32.20. and in that very day all their ambitious thoughts, and all their oppreſſive thoughts periſh; and their <hi>remembrance periſheth from the earth, and they have no name in the ſtreet,</hi> but they ſhall be <hi>forgotten as untimely births, Job</hi> 18.17. Then ſhall the good mans name, like <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod, bloſſom among the dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the reſt of the world, and his remembrance be perſpicuous. His life being diſcernable in the luſtre of it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving indeavoured to make his light ſhine among men. And verily, hereby you may know how to prevent the ſtilneſs of the Grave, the huſhneſs of Death, and the forgetfulneſs of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thean Lake, when we go hence, and ſhall be ſeen here no more: By this means we may <hi>volitare in ore piorum;</hi>
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:42531:94"/>and <hi>being dead,</hi> may <hi>yet ſpeak, Heb.</hi> 11.4. When your imitable holineſs, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, faith, godlineſs, juſtice, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, may be the inſtructers of future Generations; and they that are yet to be born, ſhall tell their Children, as an incouragement to well-doing, in what eminent acts of Grace you have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared for God; and in how great works of protection and goodneſs, God hath appeared for you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hereby you may know how to caſt Roſe-water upon your own Roſemary; how to perfume your own relicts, better then by the coſtly oyntments and ſpices of the Merchant; how you may render your ſelves grateful and acceptable to the remembrance of good Men, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and God himſelf: for by this means is <hi>Noahs</hi> name honourably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred by the holy God, many hundred years after he had ſlept with his Fathers in the Grave, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By this means you may know how to prevent the ill-husbandry of your Heirs, and to raiſe up better Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars to the perpetuating of your names then that of <hi>Abſalom.</hi> A certain Judge
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:42531:95"/>of this Land lying on his death-bed, making his Will, wherein he bequeath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed great poſſeſſions to his Son; ſaid of them, <hi>Nunc mea, nunc hujus, &amp; poſtea neſcio cujas:</hi> which words of his prov'd ſomething prophetical, there being ſcarce any thing left of thoſe large poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions to the fourth Generation. So uncertain, ſo very uncertain a mean is acquired wealth, to continue our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories to the remaining world; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how much better is it to have thy name regiſtred among the Acts and Monuments of good men, then to rear up material Monuments to our ſelves, or to have our names continued by a doubtful Poſterity?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hereby you may know how to ſave your Executors the labour, and coſt too, of going to <hi>Rome</hi> for a Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. There is an eaſier, readyer, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way to do it, and that without wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either the Popes pleaſure or leiſure: there be many in his Catalogue of Saints, that are not ſo in mens thoughts, and there's reaſon to believe neither in Gods court-roll; not there, where thoſe names are written which are written in Heaven. But thoſe who
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:42531:95"/>in the Popes Hag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ography are exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Heaven, many of them may be fear'd to be caſt down to Hell; and ſome of thoſe rais'd up to Heaven, whom he hath curſt with bell, book and candle. But whoſoever by an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right life, hath written himſelf a Saint, in the acknowledgement of his own conſcience, and of good men, ſhall finde it alſo ſo written in <hi>the Lambs book of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, hereby, on the contrary part, you may be informed,</p>
            <p n="1">1. How vile it is to bury our ſelves in a dunghil, and make the ſtench of our corruption more noiſome then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it would be, by an unproſitable life; when we do not onely render our ſelves not deſired, by being uſeleſs in our Generation; but are, as it were, kickt out of the world by our Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as a cumber and burthen to the earth we tread on; when we are onely conſulting how to eat, and drink, and ſport our ſelves; and are like the fatted Swine, whoſe death is deſired, becauſe then onely profitable: When men neither by any uſeful imployment increaſe their own wealth, nor by
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:42531:96"/>any acceptable quanties ingage the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of others, but are like <hi>ſmoke to the eyes</hi> of thoſe which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with, by crabbed conditions, and by prodigality and ill-husbandry have with their own hands buryed their Eſtates, they may well expect like a Candle which hath firſt conſumed all its own fat, to go out in a ſtink, and as they deſerve, like <hi>Coniah,</hi> to be <hi>buried with the burial of an aſs;</hi> ſo will their memories be ſoon as rotten as their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trified corpſe; and inſtead of that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balming of a <hi>good name,</hi> which is <hi>better then precious oyntment,</hi> their remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance ſhall be abominable to their own, and noiſome to all that are good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How deteſtable is it by a debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed life to render your Poſterity aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of your remembrance, when you burn a brand of repreach upon your ſucceeding Generations by unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome acts; ſo that they bluſh to hear your name mentioned, and wiſh that your memories might be buried with a ſpeedy oblivion. The Law ſaith, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.2. that <hi>a baſtard ſhall not enter into the tabernacle of the Lord to the tenth
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:42531:96"/>generation.</hi> And verily, how often is it that the Generations to come very long after, are reproached with thoſe acts of uncleanneſs, oppreſſion, cruelty, and villany, which were committed by the Fore-fathers! and as is ſaid, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.7. of love, that <hi>many waters cannot quench it, neither can the flouds drown it; if a man would give all the ſubſtance of his houſe for love, it would be utterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned:</hi> So may we ſay, that no coſt can purchaſe off this blot; no expence, no Heroick worth of Poſterity can purge away this reproach; but like a fretting canker it eats through the moſt ſolid Marbles, and leaves an uglineſs which no hand can mend; a filth which no ſope, no nitre can waſh off; a ſtench that all the odors of <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia</hi> cannot prevent the odious reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How abominable a thing it is, to be the patterns of notorious wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs to the Generations to come, and have your names regiſtred among the black Regiment of thoſe who have been the Bell-weathers to the reſidue of the World, to lead them forth into thoſe actions which are facinorous; when
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:42531:97"/>like <hi>Jeroboam the ſon of Nebat</hi> (who is ſo often mentioned in Scripture, as a curſed pattern of impiety and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry to the Kings that followed) you ſhould be remembred as the authors of wickedneſs to others. As <hi>Cain,</hi> who though ſo many thouſand of years ſince, yet is recorded as the firſt <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh</hi> 3.12. For as thoſe mens names are worthily hiſtoried, who have been patterns of well-doing to the reſidue of the world (as that <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> of <hi>Greenwich,</hi> who is memoris'd as being the firſt in the reſurrection of good works, after the demoliſhing of Abbies, building the firſt Almſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days:) So is it the juſt demerit of thoſe, who by wicked practices have led the van in that black Legion of evil doers, that they ſhould have their names branded to Poſterity; and be, as it were, hang'd up in the chains of a juſt deteſtation, for the terror of others. Hence is it that in Divine ſtory <hi>Chams</hi> impiety is both recorded and accurſed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. How lamentable is it, by notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wickedneſs to entail curſes upon our Poſterities, which they may ſmart
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:42531:97"/>for, either with us, as <hi>Corah, Numb.</hi> 16.3. <hi>Achan, Joſh.</hi> 7.24. or after we are dead and gone, as <hi>Jehoram,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.25. when not onely we bring a ſpeedy deſtruction upon our Children, as it fared with <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> from whom was <hi>cut off, him that piſſed againſt the wall, ſo that of him there was none ſhut up nor left,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 15.29. But alſo burn thoſe marks of Divine vengeance, which are never worn out, as <hi>Gehazies</hi> leproſie <hi>cleaving to his poſterity for ever,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 5.27. and Gods curſe upon <hi>Elies</hi> Houſe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.31. which you may ſee ſadly felt, by the following Generations, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.18, 19. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.27. And hence it comes to paſs, that Poſterities, though leſs flag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tious, yet approving the ſins of their Fore-fathers, do ſmart under thoſe ſevere judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which the Fathers enormities juſtly merited; yea, and ſometimes too, when they have been forgiven to the Progenitors; as the ſins of <hi>Manaſſes</hi> required of his Poſterity, though par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned to him. And from this cauſe it is, that ſome Parents do not onely prove cheats to their Poſterities, leaving
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:42531:98"/>then ſhews onely, inſtead of ſubſtances, while they leave them ill gotten goods, which like Pillars of Salt quickly reſolve into water, and flect away from thoſe that poſſeſſed them; but they do alſo (as it were) kindle a fire in their own Houſes, and lay trains for the blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of their Families; when the curſe of God juſtly due for their ſins, like a Fire long in kindling, breaks out at laſt, to the utter ruine of their Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, and ſubverſion of thoſe deſignes of greatneſs and perpetuity which they had imagined. Hence we ſee thoſe ſtately Structures built, that they might be the Manſion houſes for their following Generations, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>called after their own names,</hi> either quickly changing their owners, who by ill-husbandry and riot throw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the mouths of greedy U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers, or elſe Gods ſevere judgements of the Sword or Peſtilence, ſoon root them out thence, and in a few years 'tis ſcarce remembred that any ſuch had a being there. Sin being of the nature of that leproſie ſpoken of, <hi>Lev.</hi> 14.44. which will not be cleanſed, till <hi>the
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:42531:98"/>houſe be broken down, and the ſtones thereof, the timber and the morter be thrown out into an unclean place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Application of the Text may be to exhort us,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To lay our ſelves decently in our Graves. It was the ambition of the Ancients, that at their death, they might lay down their bodies in comely po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures. And even they that laid violent hands upon themſelves, were chiefly ſolicitous in this, that they might not fall ſo, as to become an unſeemly ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle. Thus far certainly the ſame minde concerns us all, that we go not out of the world in an uncomely man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: not wallowing in our own vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, nor hurried hence with our own luxury and intemperance, and as it were dig our own Graves with our diſorders; cutting aſunder the thred of our lives, which otherwiſe 'tis probable might be much longer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted: For our lives are ſhort of themſelves, but much ſhorter do we make them by our exceſſes; when we quench our natural heat by ſlouds of
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:42531:99"/>intemperance, and contract thoſe diſeaſes, which like an eager canker ſoon devour us, or elſe deprive our ſelves of our own reaſon, becoming ſots; and burying our underſtandings before our bodies; or in diſtempered fits expoſing our ſelves to dangers and precipices, to the breaking of our necks, or otherwiſe haſtening our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partures.</p>
            <p>For what more direful ſight can there be, then to ſee a man not made a brute onely by his ſlot, but that comely body which God hath given, rendred moſt ugly and deformed; and either carbonadoed with hotter luſts, or inflamed with hotter drinks, or diſcerpt and mangled with inhumane wounds, and carv'd out before their burials, as a fitter feaſt for worms?</p>
            <p>But it more concerns us, that we do not by wicked and nefarious acts, expoſe our ſelves to a dedecorous and ſhameful end, as the juſt guerdon of our demerits; and become an horrid ſpectacle to all but our very enemies, when even thoſe good men, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the juſtice exerciſed on us,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:42531:99"/>yet abhor the thoughts of us, and our wickedneſs, which brought upon us ſo ſevere a vengeance; our relations re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning with ſhame on their faces, wiſhing that our lives had never been, rather then ſo ended.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, how much more happy are they, who lay themſelves down in the bed of honour, ending their lives in ſome noble explots, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in though death prevented them of a triumph, yet have triumphed over death its ſelf, leading it captive, and out-living their Funerals; imploying future ages in prolix diſcourſes, to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate their worth, and publick-ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritedneſs: The ſence of this made the <hi>Spariane</hi> women taking leave of their ſons and friends going to battel, wiſh that they might either receive them alive as Conquerors, with applauſe; or elſe with joy follow their Funerals, as of thoſe who had valiantly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended their lives in their countries defence. It being, in their opinions, the firſt degree of happineſs to live uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, the ſecond to dye valiantly, and ſo honourably.</p>
            <pb n="198" facs="tcp:42531:100"/>
            <p>And therefore when we hear of thoſe who have expended their lives in ſome worthy enterpriſe for their Countries defence, in ſome notable diſcovery of unknown Regions, or in ſome magnanimous act of fortitude, conſtancie, juſtice or equity, in ſome general calamity, tumult, or epidemical madneſs: We cannot but congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late their worth, though we bemoan their miſhap, and proſecute their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equies, at how great a diſtance how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, with our acknowledgement and admiration of their merit; though caſt over-board, it may be into the Ocean; or torn in pieces by the roaring Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non; or overwhelmed with ſome breach; or expos'd to the Fowls of the Air, or Beaſts of the Field, in ſome far remote Country; or devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the inhumane mouths of greedy Canibals: yet we acknowledge, that though they were buried ignobly, yet they departed ſtrenuouſly, and took their leave of the world, not as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ones, diſgracefully kickt out of it; but as thoſe, who left behinde them deſires of them, and have that
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:42531:100"/>honourable interment in the mindes of thoſe who are virtuous, which they were denyed by the iniquity of their preſent fortunes: and though we wiſh that our <hi>exit</hi> out of the world may be more ſucceſsful yet we cannot but wiſh that it may be no leſs glorious. Hence we emulate <hi>Sampſon,</hi> though buryed under the ruines of that great Palace, becauſe in his fall he was fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged of Gods and his enemies. And we rather approve of the death of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> though <hi>ſlain by the Sword of the children of Ammon</hi> refuſing to <hi>lye with his wife</hi> on <hi>Davids</hi> motion; then if he had melted away in the ſoftneſs, and eaſe, and indulgence of his beloved <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.11. And without doubt, thoſe holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs when they expired in torments, being conſumed in the flames, and (as it were, tranſlated out of this world in a fiery Chariot) ſent their beholders back with wonder at their Faith and Conſtancie, and ſecret wiſhes that they might be enabled by Gods Grace to bear ſo great and ſharp a brunt, and by ſuch a death to glorifie God.</p>
            <pb n="200" facs="tcp:42531:101"/>
            <p>For which cauſe, we read in Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick ſtory of thoſe who upon ſuch Spectacles, <hi>ultro ſe cruciatibus obtule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt;</hi> publickly profeſſing themſelves Chriſtians, and expoſing themſelves to the tormentors cruelty; and as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>not accepting deliverance, that they might receive a better reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To go out of the world perfumed with the excellent odor of a good name; that like <hi>Demetrius,</hi> 3 <hi>Joh.</hi> 12. we may have <hi>a good report of all men, and of the truth its ſelf.</hi> A good report,</p>
            <p n="1">1. For thy devoutneſs toward God. Nothing more ornaments our perſons, nor credits our names, then holineſs: for though it often expoſe us to the ſcorn and deriſion of naughty men, yet thoſe, while they ſcoff and deride the good, ſecretly admire and honor them; there being that luſtre and brightneſs in holineſs, that though it dazzle the eyes of the perverſe, ſo that they hate to look upon it, yet they cannot but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge its beauty, and reverence thoſe whoſe faces are made illuſtrious by it:
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:42531:101"/>For we obſerve, that there is impreſt upon the nature of man, an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of that which is good, to be good, though their corrupt affections and luſts will not let them comply with that good they know; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, they hate thoſe that do, as the publick reprovers of their vice; the rectitude and uprightneſs of good men as a rule, being applyed to their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquity, diſcovering their exorbitancie and tranſgreſſion: yet what their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eſteem of holineſs is, may be calculated by the impreſſion it makes upon their mindes, manifeſted by thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Captains at <hi>Ramoth-Gilead,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9. who, while they call the Son of the Prophet <hi>a mad fellow,</hi> after the wicked gaiſe of their deboiſt Tongues; yet ſhew what eſtimation they had of him, in that as ſoon as they knew his Meſſage, they preſently <hi>haſte and blow with trumpets, proclaiming Jehu is King;</hi> a buſineſs of that import, as would have coſt every one of them their lives, if it had not ſucceeded, and therefore requiring mature deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration, though it appears not
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:42531:102"/>thought of before. And hence we may obſerve, how far even a ſhew of holineſs in that Impoſtor <hi>Mahomet</hi> prevailed to attract followers. And in later times in <hi>Africa,</hi> what feats the <hi>Scrifii</hi> effected by the ſame means; making themſelves, from poor School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, to be the abſolute Commanders of the moſt rich and flouriſhing Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries there.</p>
            <p>But how much more excellent fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grancie hath an holy life in the noſtrils of all thoſe that are truely godly, who cannot but proſecute with all affection thoſe, who in the remoteſt parts of the world, they hear are in this kinde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary; their memorial being as a ſweet-ſmelling Noſe-gay, which they deſire often to repeat the ſent of; and in the recordation of their vertue, take no little delight, having their graces actuated, and made more lively, by the remembrance of their faith and good works. And here you may ſee, how excellent it is to be one of the Stars in the Firmament of Gods Church, to ſhine like a light in the world; to be of publick conduct and direction to
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:42531:102"/>others: ſo that our death ſhould be like the fall of the General of an Army, not of a private concern, but publick loſs; when our departure is like the Eclipſe of the Sun, which leaves men in a maze, and ſeems to bode ſome gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral calamity.</p>
            <p>And this is the more, as we are of more general uſe, and frand in the way of ſervice to others; when we are <hi>as a candle ſet in a candleſtick, to give light to them that are in the houſe,</hi> the leſs of the family, or the greater of the Church and Kingdom. How deſervedly therefore did <hi>Jeremiah and all Judah mourn for Joſiah, and all the ſinging men and the ſinging women ſpake of him in their lamentations, and made it an ordinance,</hi> that they ſhould lament him, becauſe of <hi>his goodneſs, according to all that was written in the law of the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 35.25 26.</p>
            <p>But this is yet more perſpicuous, when it is <hi>a light ſhining in a dark place,</hi> when a man appears illuſtrious in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Religion, though the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of the world lye in profound ignorance and profaneneſs; when like
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:42531:103"/>
               <hi>Noah</hi> we are found <hi>upright,</hi> when <hi>all fleſh had corrupted their way before God, Gen.</hi> 6.12. 7.1. And like righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Lot</hi> in the midſt of a wicked <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> when the <hi>whole City from every quarter</hi> appear in notorious violence, and unnatural luſt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. When like <hi>Elijah,</hi> we are <hi>very jealous for the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> then, when we think our ſelves <hi>onely left.</hi> From which cauſe, we ſee how precious the names are, of <hi>Peter Waldo, John Hus, Jerome of Prague, Wickliff, Martin Luther,</hi> and others, who were like Sparks of ſhining Diamonds amidſt the dark and ruder rubbiſh of the reſt of the world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For our ſobriety toward our ſelves, for our temperance, moderation, continencie, that we have known what is that golden mean, that <hi>debita pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portio,</hi> which doth not run out into drunkenneſs, luxary, gluttony, or whatſoever is in the exceſs of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity: Nor yet that covetouſneſs which doth deny the lawful uſe of thoſe things which God hath given us. Neither melting in jovialities, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd with too much moroſity; not
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:42531:103"/>precipitately haſty, nor delatorily flow; not ſquandringly profuſe, nor chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly detaining; but behaving our ſelves like <hi>Adam</hi> in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> in the midſt of our enjoyments, having our Weights and Meaſures by us; allowing our ſelves ſuch a quantity, as right rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and our conveniences, require of us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For our righteouſneſs towards men, that we have behaved our ſelves towards all others, in all things, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all thoſe rules which juſtice doth require, being careful to perform the duties lying up on us, in the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral relations wherein we ſtand to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. As we are general Citizens of the world, that we give every one his due, <hi>honour to whom honour, fear to whom fear;</hi> to viſit the ſick, cloath the naked, relieve the neceſſirous, right the oppreſſed, bear with the weak, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain the ſtranger, give drink even to an enemy: that every creature hath taſted of your juſtice; your cattle grieve that they have loſt ſo good a Maſter, when, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, you have been <hi>merciful to your beaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="206" facs="tcp:42531:104"/>
            <p>If you are Husbands, leave a name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde you, that you did <hi>love your wives,</hi> as <hi>bone of your bone, and fleſh of your fleſh;</hi> that you <hi>gave honour to them as the weaker veſſels:</hi> That you <hi>provided things honeſt before all men; living with them according to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> and <hi>furthering their faith and joy, as being heirs together of the grace of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you be Wives, leave a name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde you, like thoſe ancient holy Women mentioned, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4. that your care was not to trick up your bodies, but <hi>adorn your ſouls</hi> with habits of vertue; and to be perſpicuous in the ornament of <hi>a meek and quiet ſpirit, which in the ſight of God is of great price;</hi> that your plots were not how you ſhould ſpend the day, or what tacling diſcourſe you ſhould have at the next idle viſit; but that you did <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider a field and buy it with the fruit of your hands:</hi> that your lives were not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with murmurings, and querulous clamours; but that you did <hi>open your mouth in wiſedom, and that in your tongue was the law of kindeneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="207" facs="tcp:42531:104"/>
            <p>If you are Parents, leave a name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde you, that you <hi>brought your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren up in the fear and nurture of the Lord;</hi> that you did not go before yours with the dark Lanthorn of a looſe and profane converſation, but that you did <hi>ſhine</hi> before them, in that holy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplarineſs, whereby you might be a pattern to them of purity, and an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life.</p>
            <p>If you are Maſters, leave a name behinde you, that you always had a ſenſe upon you, that you alſo <hi>had a maſter in heaven;</hi> to whom you muſt give an account: that it was your care, not only that your ſervants ſhould ſerve you, but they ſhould <hi>ſerve the Lord;</hi> and had rather they ſhould looſe a days work, then that God ſhould looſe an hours ſervice.</p>
            <p>If you be Magiſtrates, let not your dead hands ſmell of bribes; but let it be ſaid, that vice was your utter enemy, which neither for fear or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection you would ſhew any counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but that you made it your buſineſs to be <hi>an incourager of thoſe that do well, and a terrour unto evil doers.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="208" facs="tcp:42531:105"/>
            <p>As thou art a Subject, let it be ſaid of thee, that thou wer't none of thoſe who did <hi>ſpeak evil of dignities,</hi> nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedſt to yeild a ready complyance to any of thoſe burthens, which may conduce to thy Princes honour, and thy Countries welfare: but didſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult for all ſuch things, as make for general good, and publick peace.</p>
            <p>If men ſpeak of you, as you are a member of the Church, let them cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate thy obedience to thoſe that had the rule over thee in the Lord: That thou wert not factious, but as thou <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeſt for the faith once delivered to the Saints;</hi> ſo thou wert careful not to break the golden chain of brotherly love, for the ſcruples of opinion, but tookſt care to preſerve the <hi>unity of the faith in the bond of peace;</hi> being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd that there is more prudence to overlook groſs infirmities, then to be apt to ſeparate; and that there is more Chriſtianity in amending our private faults, then in reprehending publick e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normities: Having always ſuch a converſation as is becoming Godlineſs,
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:42531:105"/>and not denying thy Chriſtianity by thy works. Thus to go out of the world, is to carry baskets of all ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmelling Flowers along with you, to caſt into your grave; and put Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary into the hands of thoſe who do accompany your Funeral; and give a kinde of immortality to your own memorial.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:42531:106"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42531:106"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE BOOK.</head>
            <list>
               <item>ADvice concerning Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as it includes the care to ſave a mans own ſoul <hi>Page. 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cautions concerning Religion in that ſenſe <hi>Page. 7, 8, 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Religion, as it includes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion towards God <hi>Page. 10, 11, 12, 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Vertues requiſite in an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice <hi>Page. 14</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42531:107"/>
               <item>Of Veracity <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Fidelity <hi>Page. 15, 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Temperance <hi>Page. 17</hi> to <hi>22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Taciturnity <hi>Page. 22,</hi> to <hi>31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Affability <hi>Page. 31, 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Frugality <hi>Page. 33,</hi> to <hi>33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Induſtry <hi>Page. 38,</hi> to <hi>41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the choice of Company <hi>Page. 42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the danger of ill Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Page. 43, 44, 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Directions for the choice of Company <hi>Page. 46,</hi> to <hi>53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Converſation with Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liars <hi>Page. 53,</hi> to <hi>60</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Diſcourſe <hi>Page. 60,</hi> to <hi>65</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the choice of Recreations <hi>Page. 65,</hi> to <hi>78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of converſe with men <hi>Page. 78,</hi> to <hi>95</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of ſetting up a Trade <hi>Page. 95,</hi> to <hi>98</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Servants <hi>Page. 99,</hi> to <hi>108</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Marriage <hi>Page. 108,</hi> to <hi>111</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42531:107"/>
               <item>Of the choice of a Wife <hi>Page. 112,</hi> to <hi>129</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Behaviour to a Wife <hi>Page. 129,</hi> to <hi>143</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Houſe keeping <hi>Page. 143,</hi> to <hi>150</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Children their Nurſes <hi>Page. 150</hi> to <hi>153</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of their Education <hi>Page. 153,</hi> to <hi>166</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of their diſpoſing into the World <hi>Page. 166,</hi> to <hi>170</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Funerals and Alms deeds <hi>Page. 170,</hi> to <hi>173</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe on the worth of a good name <hi>Page. 175,</hi> to the end.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:42531:108"/>
            <head>Books lately printed for <hi>Hen. Everſden.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>THe Pens dexterity compleated:</hi> Or, Mr. <hi>Rich</hi> his Short-hand now perfectly taught. Prince 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theodulia:</hi> Or, a juſt Defence of hearing the Sermons, and other Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the preſent Miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> By <hi>J. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Friendly debate,</hi> Third and Fourth parts: at 4 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> bound.</p>
            <p>A Crew of kinde <hi>London</hi> Goſſips, all met to be merry, complaining of their Husbands: with their Husbands Anſwer in their own defence. To which is added, Ingenious Poems, or Wit and Drollery: at 1 <hi>s.</hi> bound.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pearls of Eloquence:</hi> Or the School of Complements.</p>
            <p>A ſerious Examination of the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents Catechiſm; and therein, of the Nonconformity to, and Separation from the Church of <hi>England.</hi> By <hi>Benj. Camfield.</hi> Price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42531:108"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
